<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ho thésauros en ostrakinois skeuesin. A pearl in an oyster-shel: or, pretious treasure put in perishing vessels. The sum or substance of two sermons preached at Withall-Chappel in Worcestershire. Wherein is set forth the mightiness of the Gospel, the meanness of its ministration. Together with a character of Mr. Thomas Hall, his holy life and death. By Richard Moore, a willing, though a most unworthy servant of God in the Gospel of his Son Jesus Christ.</title>
            <author>Moore, Richard, 1619-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51245</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37760</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51245)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37760)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1783:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ho thésauros en ostrakinois skeuesin. A pearl in an oyster-shel: or, pretious treasure put in perishing vessels. The sum or substance of two sermons preached at Withall-Chappel in Worcestershire. Wherein is set forth the mightiness of the Gospel, the meanness of its ministration. Together with a character of Mr. Thomas Hall, his holy life and death. By Richard Moore, a willing, though a most unworthy servant of God in the Gospel of his Son Jesus Christ.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Richard, 1619-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 117, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for Tho. Parkhurst at the Bible and three Crowns, near Mercers Chappel in Cheapside,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final three p. are an advertisement of books to be sold by Parkhurst.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:</p>
                  <p>A PEARL IN AN Oyſter-ſhel: OR, Pretious Treaſure put in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Veſſels.</p>
                  <p>The Sum or Subſtance of two Sermons Preached at <hi>Withall-</hi>Chappel in <hi>Worceſterſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein is ſet forth the Mightineſs of the Goſpel, the meanneſs of its miniſtration.</p>
                  <p>Together with a Character of Mr. <hi>Thomas Hall,</hi> His Holy LIFE and DEATH.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Richard Moore,</hi> a willing, though a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Servant of God in the Goſpel of his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and three <hi>Crowns,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1675.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To my much-honoured Friend</hi> Thomas Jolly, <hi>Eſquire, High-Sheriff for the County of</hi> Stafford, <hi>Juſtice of the Peace for</hi> Worceſter-ſhire, <hi>and Captain of the Train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in the ſame.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Dedication of Books to Perſons of Integrity &amp; Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, hath been of antient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the Church of Chriſt. Saint <hi>Luke</hi> had his <hi>Theophilus,</hi> a man of <note place="margin">Luke 1. Acts 1.</note> power and preheminence, whoſe Name he preſcribeth to his Books of the New Teſtament. Indeed few ſuch Stars have remained fixed in the Churches Firmament; Piety being often over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born by State-policy: too many are of <hi>Gallio</hi>'s mind, they care not to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with theſe things; or as the
<pb facs="tcp:37760:3"/>
King of <hi>Navar</hi> ſaid, They will go no further in this Sea than they can come ſafe to Land. Hence <hi>not many Wiſe, not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 26. Mr. <hi>Bolton.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>many Noble are called;</hi> And ſome great by Birth, and Noble by Blood are a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious blemiſh to an honourable Houſe. Like Sepulchers they are painted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tacitus,</hi> l. 1. c. 10.</note> yet have putrefaction within; or like the Apothecaries Pills, are gilded <note place="margin">Nobilitas Heroica eſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia quaedam notabilis, &amp;c. per quam ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo fit per adoptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Dei, Sponſa Chriſti, Templum Spiritus Sancti, <hi>Greſ.</hi> Tract. de Nobil. Joh. 1.33. Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, p. 214</note> on the outſide, but have poyſon within. <hi>Intus Nero, foris Cato, Loquitur hic ut Piſo, vivit ut Galonius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That is ever the beſt in this kind, when God is the top of the kin, Religion the Root, the holy Scriptures the Rule: when the perſon is made by Adoption the Son of God, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt; this is that <hi>Heroica Nobilitas,</hi> without which all other is little worth. It is not of blood, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of Man, but of God. Hence it was that <hi>Beatus Laudovicus,</hi> would be called <hi>Lodovicus de Piſciato,</hi> rather than to take greater Titles to himſelf; Why? there he became a Chriſtian; and for this cauſe the <hi>Bereans</hi> are ſaid to be more Noble than the Men of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter born, more Gentlemen, more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:37760:3"/>
by birth or blood: this was not by <note place="margin">Act. 17.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſiores, <hi>Beza.</hi>
                     </note> reaſon of Naturals or Morals, but for their ſpiritual Regeneration, readineſs to receive the Goſpel, and their ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings into the Scriptures daily.</p>
                  <p>Now (Noble Sir) the Kings Majeſty hath conferred a double Honour upon you in making you his High Sheriff of his Counties of <hi>Worceſter</hi> &amp; <hi>Stafford</hi> for two years together. It put me in mind of what was ſaid concerning <hi>Mordecai; What ſhall be done to the man that the King</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heſth. 6.6.</note> 
                     <hi>delighteth to honour?</hi> Since therefore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion comes not by Purchaſe, but by <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.6.</note> Providence; and all Dignity confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God, calls for Duty from Man; Go on, Sir, to do worthily in <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tah,</hi> and be famous in <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> like a true plant of Renown growing in the <note place="margin">Ruth 4.11.</note> Churche's Garden, and gathering ſtrength by being incorporated into this Body, and by receiving nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the true Root; walking in the fear of God, growing in favour with your Prince, and getting further friendſhip with his People, by your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to do good, and by being rich in good works, willing to communicate; thereby, laying up for your ſelf a good <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 18.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37760:4"/>
foundation for time to come; And in a word, improve your power againſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtors, who go about to impugn and oppoſe the Divine Authority of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> the Philoſopher, was wont to ſay, that a man ſhould lay up ſuch proviſions as in a ſhipwrack might ſwim <note place="margin">Plut.</note> out with him, ſuch Treaſures as may paſs and be current in another world, and will follow a man thither<hi>:</hi> So treaſure up the Word of God contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing precepts, promiſes and prohibitions in the table of your heart, that you may with that good Houſholder <hi>bring forth out of your treaſury things new and old.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this was one end I propoſed to <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 52</note> my ſelf, in the Dedication of theſe my mean firſt-fruits to you; which come abroad, not ſo much by a voluntary choice, as by a kind of neceſſity to mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife (I may ſo ſpeak) a poor <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brion,</hi> that otherwiſe would have lien as dead in its Mothers womb; As alſo to ſtir up your pure mind, to a ſerious ſearch and enquiry into the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. which are the invariable Canon of Truth, the Cubit of the Sanctuary, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Irenaeus.</note> the wiſe mans Star to lead to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37760:4"/>
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, the Bible is a Phyſitians <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> In the life of <hi>Baſil.</hi>
                     </note> Shop of Preſervatives againſt poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Hereſies, a patern of profitable Laws againſt rebellious Spirits, a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of coſtly Jewels againſt beggarly Elements, and a Fountain of moſt pure water ſpringing up unto Everlaſting Life.</p>
                  <p>Men of Nobleſt Birth and Royal Blood, recorded in Hiſtory Sacred or Civil, have highly prized the Word, and preferred it before their outward Priviledges and Poſſeſſions.</p>
                  <p>King <hi>David</hi> counted it more to be deſired than refined Gold, and Honey <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 10 Pſal. 119. 72. Job 23. 12</note> from the Honey-Comb. <hi>Job</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man of the Eaſt, eſteemed it more than his daily Bread and bodily Food. Our King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, when he was Crowned, they put three Swords into his Hand; he ſaid, there was one yet wanting, the Word of God, the Sword of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, was ſaid, to ſet his Crown upon the Bible. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Elder, to write the New Teſtament with his own hand, which he counted a choice Jewel. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Younger, learned much of the Scripture by heart;
<pb facs="tcp:37760:5"/>
as alſo the Lord <hi>Thomas Cromwel</hi> did. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed Memory, kiſſed the Bible preſented to her, and laid <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Speeds</hi> Chron. c. 24. p. 838.</note> it to her breaſts, and ſaid, it had ever been her delight, ſhew would frame her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment according to it. The Lady <hi>Jane Grey</hi> in her Letter that ſhe left her Siſter <hi>Katharine,</hi> ſaith of the Greek Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this is a Book which though it be not garniſhed with Gold, yet it was <note place="margin">See her Letter. Acts and Monum.</note> in wardly more pretious than Rubies; It is the Law of the Lord, the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment left to us wretches, which will lead you in the paths of eternal Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Time would fail me, if I ſhould go about to ſhew you what account the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Confeſſors and Martyrs of Jeſus <note place="margin">Sacrae Scripturae tui ſunt ſanctae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciae mei, <hi>Auguſtin.</hi>
                     </note> Chriſt made of the Scriptures; As alſo our famous Orthodox, Modern Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> left theſe Verſes behind him, written upon his Bible.</p>
                  <l>This ſacred Volume in whoſe precious leaves</l>
                  <l>The Myſteries of Heaven in treaſures lie;</l>
                  <l>The Object and the Subject of each Chriſtian eye,</l>
                  <l>Who lives by this, by death ſhall never die.</l>
                  <l>Here ſhines the Sun of grace diffuſing wide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37760:5"/>
His quickning rays on all from ſide to ſide.</l>
                  <l>Here God and Man do both embrace each other,</l>
                  <l>Met in one Perſon, Heaven and Earth do kiſs.</l>
                  <l>Here a pure Virgin doth become a Mother,</l>
                  <l>Who bore that Son, who the worlds Father is.</l>
                  <l>Here true bliſs cometh flying from on high,</l>
                  <l>To hawl Man out of Hells dark Empiry.</l>
                  <p>John a Wigord.</p>
                  <p>Take one taſte of thoſe few among the many famous verſes written by Mr. <hi>Clark.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">See his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poem or Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, p. 622. In his Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror.</note>
                  </p>
                  <l>This Book, theſe Sentences, theſe Lines,</l>
                  <l>Each Word and Letter,</l>
                  <l>To me is better,</l>
                  <l>Than Chains of Pearl and golden Mines.</l>
                  <l>'Tis Heaven tranſcrib'd and glory pen'd,</l>
                  <l>Gods Truth no doubt</l>
                  <l>Was copied out,</l>
                  <l>When he this Gift to man did ſend,</l>
                  <p>J. C.</p>
                  <p>You ſee, Sir, with what a Cloud of Witneſſes you are compaſſed about, for your conduct &amp; incouragement in your way towards <hi>Canaan</hi> your heavenly Country, that you may taſte of the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:37760:6"/>
Mannah, and read and rumina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> upon this Bread of Life, and Food <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> your Faith: And as by much porin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and pondering upon the Statute-Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the Land you may become a wiſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> able Juſticiary; ſo hereby a true an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intelligent Chriſtian, and the better ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quainted with your own heart: For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Scriptures are ſo penned (as <hi>Athanaſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſaith) that every man may think the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeak, <hi>de ſe in re ſua,</hi> of him in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Affairs. Indeed there is little good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be got by reading the Scriptures curſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rily and careleſly, but if you do it duel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and diligently with attention, affectio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and ſupplication, they will have ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> influence upon the Soul, and ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face upon <hi>Luke.</hi>
                     </note> efficacy, as is to be received from no o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Book that can be named<hi>:</hi> hereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> how hath the proud heart been humbled the hard heart ſoftned, thoſe boiſterou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and predominant paſſions and affection ſubdued, and every thought captivate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into the Obedience of Chriſt; ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Man hath become of a Lion a Lamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of a Leopard a Lamb, of a Swine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sheep.</p>
                  <p>Who ſees not at this day, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nauſeating of this Bread of Life hath
<pb facs="tcp:37760:6"/>
brought many men to ſpiritual leanneſs, ſet them upon dangerous precipices of pride, till they have fallen into the dead ſea of practical Atheiſm; whereas a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſearching out of the Will of God revealed in his Word, is an effectual <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingfleet</hi> in his Epiſt. to <hi>Origin. Sacrae.</hi>
                     </note> means for the maintaining a powerful ſenſe of Religion in the ſouls of men. Be ſure therefore to make a diligent ſearch into the mind of God, as it is here manifeſted; For the dignity of the Scriptures, and the Majeſty of Chriſt, who is the Author and the matter of them, mutually look one upon another as the Sun doth on the Stars, and the Stars on the Sun: for as the excellency of the Sun appears by the glory of the Stars, to which it giveth light; ſo the Majeſty of Chriſt is manifeſt in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, to which he giveth credit: And as the Pearl by the often beating of the Sun-beams upon it, becomes glorious; ſo we by beholding, as in this Glaſs, the Glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 18.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>It happily may be expected from ſome, according to the Cuſtom of ſuch <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 10, 11, 13.</note> Dedications, that I ſhould ſpeak of your
<pb facs="tcp:37760:7"/>
perſonal worth; but I well know your modeſty would by this means be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the bluſh, and ſome disaffected perſons might count me a paraſite: I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turn ſuch Praiſes into Prayers, that he who is able to make all grace abound in every good Work, would multiply your Seed, and increaſe the Fruits of your Righteouſneſs, that others may glorifie God for your profeſſed ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Goſpel of Chriſt; this is, Sir, and ſhall be the hearty Prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Servant in the ſame Saviour,</hi> Richard Moore.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Wetherock-hill</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>Novemb.</hi> 4th 1674.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:7"/>
                  <head>To the Candid, Chriſtian Reader.</head>
                  <p>WIſe <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no end in making Books.</hi> In <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 12.</note> this Caſe, Covetouſneſs and Ambition, like the two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Horſeleech, never ſay it is <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough;</hi> and in Polemical Diſcourſes Men are endleſs in their Anſwers and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ſo that the Reader after a curious inſpection, will find many things imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, acted in paſſion, and utterly to fail his expectation; like the hungry Dog gnawing upon a Flint-ſtone, wherewith <hi>he may aſſoon</hi> (as we ſay in the Proverb) <hi>break his Neck as his Faſt;</hi> Which made <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſo ironically to paſs his Cenſure of ſuch; <hi>Multi mei ſimiles</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hoc Morbo laborant, ut cum ſcribere neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, a ſcribendo tamen temperare non poſſunt.</hi> And leſt any man ſhould ſay unto me, <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf;</hi> Know, <hi>good Reader,</hi> that the Subject-matter of this ſmall Piece, is not Controverſial, but truly Chriſtian; you have here an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Narrative of a Man of God, a Godly
<pb facs="tcp:37760:8"/>
Divine, who was illuſtrious in his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, one that thundred in his Doctrine, and lightened in his life; who was a holy Preſident to his Flock, and left many whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Precepts behind him when he died.</p>
                  <p>He was conſcious that Examples do more affect or infect, than Rule; that Practice doth obviate Precept, and that our life is a continual imitation, and that we are one anothers pattorns and temptations; that moſt men go the way that is gone, not the way that muſt be gone; and are carried by the gale of Cuſtom, rather than by the guide of Conſcience; he choſe therefore to go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Charge, in all manner of Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>He was one that was high in Parts, holy and lowly in Heart, the more he knew the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>As</hi> Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen <hi>of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius.</note> more he perceived his own ignorance: as Boughs loaded with Fruit, and full Ears with Corn, and bow down the head, and bend towards the Earth.</p>
                  <p>As for ſuch, who have the higheſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Endowments, without grace, they are but glittering Glow-worms in the dark; or as Toads which (they ſay) have a Pearl in the head, and poyſon in their whole body. The Devil deſires to be adorned with theſe counterfeit Pearls and <hi>Briſtoll-ſtones.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37760:8"/>
But this renowned Worthy had a good inſide and outſide, clean hands, a learned head, and a loyal heart to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>It were to be wiſhed, that ſuch who are <note place="margin">Juſtin Martyr. <hi>non in verbis ſed in fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis res Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis dependet.</hi> Heſiod.</note> ſo ready to ſtrive about words, would ſtrive to imitate him in good works: to imitate Vertue, is a Vertue to be imitated; and herein that is truly excellent wherein we ſtrive to excel <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, follow him, as he follows Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Now give me leave to acquaint thee <hi>(good Reader)</hi> with the occaſion of this my undertaking, I was deſired by ſome Friends to write what I knew concerning the Life of Mr. <hi>Hall,</hi> which I did with ſome unwillingneſs, and happily no leſs waywardneſs; and no wonder, for beſides my perſonal knowledg of him, and what I gathered out of his own Works, I could be informed little of him by his Friends, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept about the manner of his Death; I could neither procure to ſee the ſeveral Occurrences of his Life written by his own hand, nor a ſight of the Sermon preached at his Funeral: and hearing that his Life written by himſelf was loſt, and being loſt that one ſo well deſerving of the Church of God, ſhould not be more publickly ſpoken of, I was perſwaded to print theſe plain Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb facs="tcp:37760:9"/>
together with his Character, Life and Death; wherein happily I may expect to meet with ſome moroſe reception from the malevolent; but it matters not, <hi>contra ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophantarum morſus non eſt remedium.</hi> As touching me, it is a ſmall matter for me to be judged <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. Auguſt. <hi>cont.</hi> Faſſ. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 34.</note> mans day. <hi>Non curo illos Cenſores, qui non intelligendo reprehendunt, vel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendendo, non intelligunt:</hi> My Comfort is this, That how mean ſoever the undertaking is, yet the intenton of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is to bring honour to God and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Men. Go and do like to him.</p>
                  <p>Ibeg of thee <hi>(Courteous Reader)</hi> to pardon my boldneſs in this my undertaking, and where thou meeteſt with any <hi>Errata's,</hi> correct them with thy Pen, or cover them with a Mantle of love, conſidering with thy ſelf, <hi>Humanum eſt errare, errare poſſum, haereticum nolo eſſe;</hi> Miſtakes may be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by my diſtance from the Preſs, or through the Printers being unacquainted with my hand. <hi>Farewel</hi>
                  </p>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Horace <hi>his Epiſtle.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>—Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis Candidus imperti, ſi non his utere me-</hi>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in the deareſt Lord. <hi>Richard Moore.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37760:9"/>
                  <head>SERMON I.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>2 COR. 4. 7.</bibl>
                     <q>But we have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe great Apoſtle of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, begins the Chapter with<note place="margin">v. 1.</note> a Remonſtrance of Gods meer Mercy in calling him to the Miniſtry; in the faithful diſcharge of which, though afflicted, he will go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward without fear or fainting; and in this Caſe he commends himſelf and his Colleagues to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and hereby takes away all ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion<note place="margin">v. 2.</note> of arrogancy, in that they ſought not their own Gain, their own Glory, but<note place="margin">v. 5.</note>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 24.</note> Chriſts; not to rule over their Faith, but to relieve their Joy.</p>
                  <p>And here he ſeems to wipe off an Aſperſion of the falſe Teachers, tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the contempt of his Perſon, and the diſcredit of his Preaching: They ſeem
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37760:10"/>
charge him as if he had not light and <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 10.</note> ſight to fit and qualifie him for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Goſpel. To this St. <hi>Paul</hi> anſwers;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By way of Aſſertion; God hath<note place="margin">v. 6.</note> ſhined into our hearts, and given us out of his rich <hi>Treaſure,</hi> Wiſdom and Knowledg.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By a Conceſſion; he yields, that <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> he, and others, who were authorized by Chriſt to preach the Goſpel, and to repreſent his Perſon, were <hi>Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the words you have theſe Parts:
<list>
                        <item>1. A <hi>Precious Pearl</hi> diſpenſed, <hi>viz.</hi> The Goſpel.</item>
                        <item>2. The <hi>Stewards</hi> intruſted with it; The Apoſtles and all Faithful Paſtors. <hi>We have it.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. The great Proprietor that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates it; God who cauſeth Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs.</item>
                        <item>4. The Pots or Pipes wherein this Pearl is put; <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>in Earthen Veſſels.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. The End intended in it; that the Excellency of the Power may be of God, and not of us.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Herein the Apoſtle alludes to earthly <note place="margin">Calvin in loc.</note>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37760:10"/>
Pearls which uſually are not put into a coſtly Cabinet, but into a vile Veſſel: ſo the Lord is pleaſed to make uſe of frail miſerable men to be his Miniſters to bring their brethren to Chriſt, that his Power hereby may be the more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent.</p>
                  <p>As the Text hath reference to the foregoing Verſe, it ſeems to be a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor taken from Lanthorns; and ſo the Apoſtles did not hide their Light, that ſhined into them, but let it out to enlighten others: but according to the Original Word, it may be rendred Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels made of <hi>Oyſter-Shells,</hi> by an alluſion <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> to the Precious Pearl that is found in Shell-fiſh.</p>
                  <p>Hence you may obſerve:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Doct. <hi>That the Goſpel is a Pearl of Price, a choice Treaſure.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Chriſt Embaſſadours are Earthen Veſſels intruſted with this Treaſure.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The Goſpel ſhould not be in leſs eſteem with you, becauſe it is diſpenſed from, or in Earthen Veſſels.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>In the handling the firſt Point, I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37760:11"/>
ſhall ſhew what a Treaſure is, what kinds of Treaſures there are; What a Treaſure the Goſpel is; the Reaſons why it is ſo; and the Cauſes why worldly men do not ſo account it.</p>
                  <p>1. A <hi>Treaſure</hi> is ſomething of Price, and of account, laid up cloſely and charily, for future uſe in Cheſts or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets, in peace, from the pilfering of Thieves, and in War, from the plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Souldiers.</p>
                  <p>And it is either,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. An <hi>Earthly Treaſure,</hi> as Gold and Silver, Pearls, and precious Stones, <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 3.</note> which worldly men heap up for the laſt day, wherein they place their chief hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; yet which ſhall be as fewel to put on fire the Wrath of God againſt them. Theſe have their Names writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">Jer. 17.13. c. 41. 8.</note> in the Earth, and their Converſation; only their Treaſure is in the Field.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Heavenly <hi>Treaſure, viz.</hi> Chriſt; the Graces of the Spirit and the Goſpel, which Believers hide and hoard up in their hearts, and lay out as the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant <note place="margin">Luk. 12.33</note> upon Exchange doth his Money that he may receive it with advantage in another Country; ſo Chriſtians that are trading in, and travelling towards <note place="margin">Phil. 1.27. c. 3.20.</note>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37760:11"/>
another Country, are laying up and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out for that, where they have <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> their Burgeſs-ſhip, they live by the Laws of that Country which is <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 11.</note> Heavenly, and hide them in their hearts; <hi>Thy Word</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>have I hid in my heart.</hi> This is the <hi>Treaſure</hi> I am now to treat of. <hi>More to be deſired</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.10</note> 
                     <hi>than gold, yea than much fine gold. More precious than jewels; the price of it is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Job 28.16, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>above rubies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Goſpel is that Treaſure hid in the Field, which cannot be too far <note place="margin">Mat. 13, 44</note> fetcht, or too dear bought.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a precious <hi>Treaſure</hi> to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before thouſands of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 72.</note> it's better than precious Stones; <note place="margin">Prov. 8.11. M. Bolton Job 28. 15, 16.</note> all the Pleaſures, nay all the Treaſures in the world are not to be compared to it, though the Mountains were Pearl, and the whole Globe a ſhining Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolite.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is a heaped <hi>Treaſure,</hi> contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Multum in minimo, in parvulo;</hi> I will not compare it to <hi>Homers</hi> Iliads in a Nut-ſhel, but prefer it before all other Books, Humane or Divine: ſince it <note place="margin">Eph. 3.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> comprehends <hi>totum hominis &amp; bonum hominis;</hi> it contains in it abundance of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37760:12"/>
curious variety of the manifold Wiſdom of God; as a Ring that hath many Jewels in it, and a Treaſure that is compacted of many precious Things; for commonly a ſingle Commodity doth doth not make a Treaſure but Many.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Goſpel is a hoarded and hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Treaſure; for it contains in it thoſe <note place="margin">Col 2. 3.</note> Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg which are hidden from the wiſe and prudent men of the world, who have <hi>principium laeſum,</hi> a crackt brain, that they cannot perceive things ſpiritual. <note place="margin">1 Co. 2.14.</note> Jewels are not uſed to be put in places where they may be ſeen of every eye. What <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks concerning Wiſdom is true of the Myſteries of wiſdom and knowledg in the Goſpel; The Depth <note place="margin">Job 28. 12, 14.</note> ſaith, it is not in me, the Sea it is not in me. Such who are able to ſearch into the ſecrets of nature, and can fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom the depth of Arts and Sciences, yet are many times meer ſtrangers to it, they know not how to dig for, or to draw out this <hi>Treaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Goſpel hath an attractive vertue in it, when preached in the power of the Holy Ghoſt, to penetrate the heart, and to draw it after Chriſt:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37760:12"/>
As the Loadſtone hath a natural force to draw Iron, and the Sun to draw up Vapours; ſo the Sun of the Goſpel by the agency of the Spirit to attract the Heart. As the men of the world who have Treaſures hid in the Earth, they count them their chief happineſs, and their hearts are drawn after them; ſo the godly, who make the Goſpel their Treaſure, and their hearts are fixed to it, they will forſake all to follow it. <hi>Where your Treaſure is there will your hearts be alſo. Veniat Verbum Domini</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 6.21.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; ſubmittemus ſexcenta ſi nobis fuiſſent Colla,</hi> ſaid a <hi>Dutch</hi> Divine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe the Goſpel reveals the unſearchable Riches of the Grace of God in Chriſt, in whom are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg, whereby the Saints are inabled to lay up <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 19.</note> a good Foundation for themſelves, to lay up their Treaſure in Heaven, and to <note place="margin">Phil. 2.16.</note> lay hold of eternal Life. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.9 Tit. 1. 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. All things or perſons that excel others in their kind, and are of greateſt rate for their rarity or preciouſneſs, theſe are counted Treaſures; but ſuch is the Goſpel: as amongſt Fiſhes, The Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37760:13"/>
and in Birds, the Eagle; and a mongſt Beaſts, the Lion; and Princes and Potentates among Men, they are valued of more worth than thouſands of an inferiour rank: So in Books, thoſe which are rare and fetcht from far; As <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 3.</note> it is ſaid, That <hi>Plato</hi> gave for three choice Books 30000 Florens; How much more is the Goſpel to be prized ſince it came from Heaven, in whoſe ſacred Leaves the Myſteries of Heaven in Treaſures lie! <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Object and the Subject of each Chriſtian eye;</l>
                     <l>Who lives by this, by death ſhall never die.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="3">3. All other Creatures, how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſoever, conſume in time. Gold and Silver is ſubject to the ruſt and <note place="margin">Jam. 5. 3.</note> canker; the moſt princely Ornaments, even Crowns beſet with Pearls, and precious Diamonds, periſh in time; the beſt Books are worm-eaten; But <hi>the Word of our God, ſhall ſtand for ever.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Saints have ever eſteemed it ſo; for they have been content to part with all for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37760:13"/>
That's a mans Treaſure, which he prefers before all other things, and will part with all rather than this; As <hi>a man will part with all he hath to ſave his life:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Job 2. 4.</note> He counts Life his chief <hi>Treaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Arragon</hi> profeſſed, he would loſe his Jewels, rather than his Books; So a Child of God will part with all, rather than the Goſpel; as that <hi>Dutch</hi> Divine ſaid, as before.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That is a mans Treaſure, which he counts he cannot live without. Some count Riches their Treaſure; for if they are robbed of them, their life is unravelled, their heart and their hopes break at once, they die in the neſt as did <hi>Nabal.</hi> Some count Pleaſures their Treaſure; for if they be deprived once of them, they cry out with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian, They ſhall never be merry more.</hi> Some count Children their Treaſure; and therefore cry out with <hi>Rachel, Give me Children or elſe I die.</hi> But a Child <note place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> of God makes the Goſpel his Treaſure, for he thinks he cannot live comfortably without it. It was a remarkable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Luther,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>He could not live without the Word in Paradiſe, but with it, he could, even in Hell it ſelf.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37760:14"/>Object. <hi>But if the Word be ſo choice a Treaſure, What may be the Reaſon why the World doth not ſo eſteem it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Cauſes of this I conceive may be either in reſpect of the Organ, or of the Object.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the Organ: The Prince of the World hath caſt a miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of theſe men, that the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhineth not in their <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 4.</note> hearts: As for Example, The Sun is a glorious Body, full of light and luſtre, yet blind eyes perceive it not; So the Goſpel is a Light ſhining in darkneſs, but the blind and bruitiſh world diſcern it not, but prefer with the Cock in the Fable, a Corn of Barley before it. As one that looked intently on a curious Picture, was asked the cauſe why he did ſo? anſwered, <hi>If thou hadſt my</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Nicoſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> 
                     <hi>eye thou wouldſt no leſs admire it than I do;</hi> So had the world but an illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted eye, they would judg of the Word as the Saints do.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In reſpect of the Object. They make not the Word of GOD,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37760:14"/>
but the World the matter of their choice; Their Treaſures are in their Fields and in their Flocks and Herds; And thus <hi>they heap up Treaſures for the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>laſt day.</hi> He that holds the World his Portion, will prefer it before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A godly Man eſteems the Word of God as his Heritage for ever; and <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 11.</note> therefore takes it for a greater Treaſure than Chains of Pearl and Mines of Gold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Serves to refute the folly of a generation of Men, who are wiſer for <note place="margin">Luk. 16.8.</note> the World than for Heaven, and hoard up Treaſures for themſelves here in the place of their pilgrimage, and are not rich towards God: Is the Word ſuch a <note place="margin">Luk. 12.21.</note> Treaſure? Why do you prefer the dirt and dung of this World? The Pleaſures of Sin, and the Profits that reſult from your Purchaſes and Poſſeſſions before this Pearl of Price? Could I but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint theſe men where they might buy a cheap Piece of Ground, or where Gold and Silver, and precious Jewels lay hid in the Earth, though it were a great way off, and hard to get, Would they not hearken to me? Oh how would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37760:15"/>
they run or ride, dig and delve in the bowels of the Earth to get them! Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I acquaint you with a more precious Purchaſe, with a far more enduring Subſtance, and tell you it is nigh unto you, where it is hid, and how eaſie <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 8</note> it is to be had, yet I cannot prevail with you for my life, to take a little pains to get it, or to part with a little of that which you cannot long keep, though it were to gain that you can never loſe. Well, your Treaſure you are for, and your Treaſure (without true repentance) you will have, ſuch <note place="margin">Pſal. 140. 10.</note> as it is, ſuch as you have laid in, and <hi>laid up for your ſelves, even Treaſures of Wrath againſt the day of Wrath, and the Revelation of the righteous Judgment of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Which that you may avoid, let me prevail with you to make the Goſpel your Choice; count it your chief Good below God and Chriſt. It is a Legacy left you by your deareſt Lord, ſealed with his precious blood; herein you have a promiſe of the Pardon of Sins, of Adoption of Sons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (if you are not wanting to your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37760:15"/>
ſelves) you may become Heirs of God, and Joint-heirs with Chriſt, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Inheritance of the Saints; And will you not read it? Will you not heed it? at leaſt, with as much care as a Child would his Fathers Will, to know what he hath left him; to ſee whether ſome one or other have not a Title before him to the chief Treaſure. Alas beloved, Do we ſee it, and is it not our ſhame, that thoſe <hi>Terrae-Filii</hi> Sons of the Earth, can even ſweat for Silver, forbear Pleaſures that they may get Profit, dig deep in Mines for Precious Mettle, and choice Jewels, ſtorm dangers and difficulties by Land <note place="margin">Omnis cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditas in illum ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur.</note> and Sea; The Merchant, the Mariner, the Mathematician, the Mechanick, the Souldier, and he that ſtudies the Philoſophers-ſtone? And will you not take as much care, be at as much coſt, uſe as much courage in Chriſtianity at leaſt, in ſearching into thoſe golden Mines of the Goſpel wherein are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered <note place="margin">Joh. 5.39.</note> thoſe hidden Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith to this purpoſe, <note place="margin">In his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>Super Orat. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
                     </note> Such as dig Treaſures out of the Earth, though they get infinite Wealth,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37760:16"/>
yet give not over till they have drawn the Mine dry; for this is their chief care, not to get out much, but to leave none behind. How much more ſhould we endeavour to know the <note place="margin">Read the Lady <hi>Jane Grays</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to her Siſter.</note> whole mind of Chriſt contained in the Goſpel, lay out our ſelves about it, and labour in it day and night.</p>
                  <p>The Goſpel is a pure Treaſure, very pure, purity it ſelf, free from all droſs. Such as dig in Mines for Gold and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 140.</note> precious Mettals are willing to work hard, though the Oar hath much droſs and dirt that cleaves to it, till it be refined; but this is a pure and proved Word, pure as Silver, tried in a Furnace of Earth fined ſeven-fold. <note place="margin">Pſal. 12.6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is a perfect Treaſure in all parts without mixture of any other alloy: nothing muſt be put to it or ought be taken from it. Thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things that are taken out of the <note place="margin">Deut. 12. 32.</note> Earth, even all Mettals have their mixture, which doth ſomewhat debaſe them; but the Word of Chriſt is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> of it ſelf, and compleat without the additions or traditions of men; <hi>He that addeth to, or diminiſheth any thing</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>from it, ſhall have no part in the Book o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37760:16"/>
                     <hi>life, but ſhall partake of the plagues that are written it.</hi> Oh how inexcuſable are the Papiſts, who count it imperfect, and pollute it with the mud and Mine of their vain inventions; and carnal-Goſpellers, who profane it, who take not pains to read it, who heed it not, neither hoard it in their hearts!</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is a precious Treaſure; Gold, Silver and Jewels, are precious things, and yet they are but as the Offal and Excrements of the Earth; a man may have much of them, and yet be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ſay with <hi>Caeſar, Omnia fui &amp; nihil profuit;</hi> I have been all things and never the better; but the price of <note place="margin">Job 28. Pſal. 119. 72, 127.</note> this is above rubies, to be eſteemed as gold, nay, <hi>above fine gold, even above thouſands of gold and ſilver.</hi> Had the Lord thought theſe things a fit portion for his people, he would not have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them to his enemies; the barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Indians</hi> have much more of theſe than you.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is a profitable Treaſure; to teach, to convince; profitable for all <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> things, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſs. <hi>Gregory</hi> calls it the heart and ſoul of God. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the food
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37760:17"/>
of the Soul. St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> againſt Errors. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> the inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riable Rule of Truth. In a few words, it teacheth true godlineſs, which is profitable for all things, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. for all perſons whether in a publick or private capacity. <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is profitable for men in all Duties, in all Eſtates and Conditions, which reſpect their active or paſſive obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: It teacheth men what they ought, and what they ought not do; how to live, and how to die; and how to ſuffer, and how to carry themſelves in proſperity and adverſity. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle had never taken out that Leſſon, had he not learnt it here, <hi>viz.</hi> to be content in every eſtate, to know how <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 11.</note> to want, and how to abound; and as one that had nothing, yet poſſeſſing all <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 10.</note> things. A ſtrange hyperbolical Speech, a Riddle to the world.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It is a pleaſant Treaſure, ſweeter than Honey, yea, than the droppings <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 10 Pſal. 119. 103. Hoſ. 13.15.</note> of the Honey-combs. <hi>Ephraim</hi> who was a pleaſant Child in Gods account, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 20. yet he had the Treaſure of all his pleaſant things ſpoiled<hi>:</hi> but here is a ſweetneſs, wherewith, as the Soul
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37760:17"/>
of man ſhall never be ſatiated, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it ever be ſatisfied till it come to Heaven.</p>
                  <p>It is a laſting Treaſure, an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Sweetneſs: I might add, what I before ſaid, The Goſpel is a heaped, a hoarded, a hidden and a heavenly Treaſure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. And now you Sons of Pleaſure, and Daughters of the Horſleach, who are ſo ready to cry, <hi>Give,</hi> and are never ſatisfied; Tell me what you would have? And where you are like to mend your ſelves? You are for Profit, here is Gold for you; you are for Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and here's Honey for you. Oh how well might you be without theſe Earthly-ſweets! Would you but drink of this Well of living Waters, where only it is the deeper the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I cannot but wonder that Men that have Reaſon, and are in their right wits can hear theſe things, and not be (at the leaſt) convinced, if not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Oh that the <hi>god of this World</hi> [the Devil] ſhould be able, in things ſo clear and perſpicuous, to put a Blind upon your Underſtandings, and Bribe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37760:18"/>
your Judgments! Truly, if the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in theſe Halcyon-days, be a hidden Treaſure to you, it is ſo only to ſuch as are loſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. Beg of God by frequent and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayer, that he would give you inlightned underſtanding, ſo as you <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 18.</note> may ſee a ſingular vertue in, and may ſet a ſuperlative value upon this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Treaſure, the Goſpel; which is a manifeſtation of Gods Mind, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his Will and Wiſdom, a Copy of his Truth, a tranſcript of Heaven, and Happineſs to the Heirs of Glory. What <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> ſaith of Moral Vertue, may much more truly be ſaid of the Goſpel; If moral Vertue could <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aeneas Sylv.</hi> in his Epiſt. to <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi>
                     </note> be beheld with mortal eyes, it would work a ſtrange admiration in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders. But behold here you have Divine Vertue pointed out to the life Majeſty and Mercy, Vertue and Verity, Righteouſneſs and Peace kiſſing each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; a far greater Treaſure than the <hi>Iſhmaelitiſh</hi> Merchants had of <hi>Joſeph</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 10</note> who became Lord-Treaſurer of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> and bleſſed be the Lord that we ſhould be born to behold with our eyes the things that many Prophets and <note place="margin">Mat. 13 17.</note>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37760:18"/>
righteous men deſired to ſee, and have not ſeen them; <hi>Paulum in Ore, Chriſtum in Carne revelatum,</hi> were two of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi>'s great wiſhes<hi>:</hi> To ſee <hi>Paul</hi> in the Pulpit and Chriſt Incarnate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> came from far to ſee <hi>Solomon</hi> and to hear his Wiſdom, and parted with much precious Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for this: But behold a greater than <hi>Solomon;</hi> the great Lord-Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the whole world hath ſent his Embaſſadours to publiſh the glad-ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Peace, and to ſing that Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Hymn, <hi>Glory to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, on Earth Peace, good will towards</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Men.</hi> And yet this Treaſure ſticks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hand, and is vilely valued by the blind world, who ſee not their want, and know not the worth of a Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Wiſdom uttereth her Voice, and proclaims her precious Wares, and ſaith, <hi>How long ye ſimple ones, will you</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>love ſimplicity, and ye ſcorners delight in ſcorning!</hi> &amp;c. yet the Staple-treaſure of the Goſpel will not off; Men make light of it, who have their Treaſures <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 5.</note> in the Fields, and will hardly ſtep over their threſholds to gather this Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37760:19"/>
Could we but once perſwade you to get inlightned underſtandings, you would ſee with other eyes, and hear with other ears than you now do, and walk with other feet, and work with other hands; you would no longer lie down with the ſluggard, and ſay, <hi>O utinam boc eſſet laborare!</hi> Oh that this were to labour! you would not with the hungry man barely long for this food, but labour for it; you would not only thirſt as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Man doth after Wealth, but you would work to get it; you would wait at the Pool, and at the beautiful Gates <note place="margin">Acts 3. 2, 10.</note> of the Temple, and your main requeſt to Chriſt would be that of the blind Man, <hi>Lord, only that mine eyes might be</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mark 10. 51.</note> 
                     <hi>opened,</hi> ſaith he.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. With what Joy ſhould we embrace the Goſpel? Men uſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice when they get Treaſures. The Marriage-day upon this account, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Merry-day, becauſe the Man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects a Treaſure; for on what he ſets his heart and affections, that's his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: Shall carnal Men rejoice when they find Jewels? And ſhall not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37760:19"/>
who have a Treaſure made up <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 14.</note> of Jewels in the Goſpel rejoice even more than in all riches? We read in the Occurrences of the Low-Countries, That a day of Feſtivity was kept ſome time for joy, that the Scriptures. were tranſlated. But this joy laſted but for a ſeaſon, like unto that of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 5. 35.</note> his Hearers. And indeed, what Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>Moulin</hi> ſaith of his Countrymen, we have cauſe to ſay of ours; <hi>Time was</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Moul. Theoph. 2. 278.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>That whiles they burnt us for reading the Scriptures, we burnt with zeal to be reading of them.</hi> Now with our liberty is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed a neglect of the Word of God; and ſo it is with us as in ſome parts of the World, where there are great ſtore of Pearls and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Things, the people will part with them, for ſuch things that we here count trifles; So the Goſpel is looked upon by many, as Mannah was with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> but common Meat. Surely, were it to be ſent to ſuch as have not heard it, they would hear it more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it more, rejoice in it more than we do. Alas for this poor Nation, it ſurfeits upon the glorious Goſpel! And hence it is, ſo few with Joy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37760:20"/>
it, with Faith believe it, with their Heart embrace it. But let all that are Gods Jewels rejoice in it more than in Corn and Wine, and all earthly Comforts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. Let us come to the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel as unto a Treaſury and Store-houſe of all good things, <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 1.</note> the Common Mart and Market of all ſpiritual Proviſion, even Treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg; Here is Bread for the hungry, Water for the thirſty, Milk for Babes, ſtrong Meat for <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.2. Pſal. 104. 15.</note> Men, Wine to make glad the Heart and Oyl to make his face ſhine<hi>:</hi> Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you may have Gold to enrich you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 3.18.</note> Garment to cloath you; here are Or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naments for your head, Bracelets fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your neck and arms, Pendents for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ears, Eye-ſalve for your eyes, a Gird<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for your loins, Breſt-plates for you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hearts, and Signets for your hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> You have here a <hi>Cornucopia</hi> for Plenty a <hi>Catholicon</hi> for Cures; an <hi>Armory</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Weapons againſt ſpiritual Wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes; a <hi>Library</hi> for Books, and Treaſury for Jewels. What woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you have? What are your Wants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37760:20"/>
Here you may have a Supply from Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>In whom doth all fulneſs dwell; and from whoſe fulneſs we receive Grace for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 1.19. Joh. 1.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Grace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are you poor in ſpirit? here are du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <note place="margin">Prov. 8.10.</note> Riches for you; ſick? here is Phyſick for you; ſorrowful? here's Comfort for you; tempted? here's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Strength for you; Are you in <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> Bonds? here's Bale for you<hi>:</hi> Are you broken for ſin? here's a precious Balm for you<hi>:</hi> Have you a hard heart? here's a ſuppling and a ſoftning Oyl for you<hi>:</hi> Are you ſubject to fears and doubts? here Faith is begotten for you<hi>:</hi> Are you ſullen or ſilent, and cannot pray? here you have the Spirits Promiſe to help your Infirmities<hi>:</hi> Would you <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26. Eph. 6. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> know how to behave your ſelves in the Houſe of God? in your own Houſes, as Husbands and Wives, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants? Come <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 1.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o this publick Treaſury where theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hings are to be had: but you muſt know this, that theſe Treaſures are not to be attained without digging and Chriſtian Diligence in the uſe of means. It is a hard work to dig for Gold, and you muſt make heart-work of it. The <note place="margin">Job 3. 21.</note>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37760:21"/>
Apoſtle minds young <hi>Timothy</hi> of this, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. 13.</note> who had made it his trade from his youth, <hi>Meditate of theſe things, and give thy</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>ſelf wholly to them, that thy profiting may appear.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>If thou ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt her as Silver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid Treaſure; Then ſhalt thou underſtand</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 2.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledg of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Queſt. <hi>But what further means muſt we uſe to get this Treaſure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> You muſt be ſure to ſeek it <note place="margin">Nihil quaeritur niſi per viam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</note> in Gods ways, and in the uſe of the good means he hath appointed. As,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You muſt mix the Word with Faith in your hearts when you read it or when you hear it; for ſuch as bring not Faith along with them, depart from the Word without Fruit; <hi>The Goſpel</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>preached, profiteth not them that hear it, who mix it not with Faith.</hi> Faith in the heart is like the ſweet confection of Oyntment poured upon Chriſt his Head; it caſts a ſweet ſcent and ſavour into all the parts and powers of the Soul: it is Oyl to theſe wheels, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37760:21"/>
makes them go with agility in the ways of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Pray unto God that he would <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 18.</note> pour upon you the eye-ſalve of the Spirit; for this Treaſure lyes deep, and our ſhallow capacities cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it, our underſtandings being not only blind, but blindneſs it ſelf. <note place="margin">Eph. 1.18. Domine velamen amove, Volumen evolve.</note> Pray therefore that your underſtandings may be unvailed, that the Truths of Chriſt may be revealed, that neither the Organ may be dim, nor the Object dark; But of this I ſpake before.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Live under a godly Miniſtry, where the Word drops like pretious dew from Sion into the fertile vallies: This is the <hi>Indies</hi> where this Treaſure lies; Theſe Preachers <hi>lips preſerve know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> and you muſt <hi>ſeek the Law at</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Cant. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>their mouths, feeding your kids beſides the ſhepherds Tents.</hi> Such who are uſed to dig in Mines, know by the colour of the Sands, and by the taſte of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that run from the Mountains where the true Treaſure lieth; So you may gueſs where, and from what ſort of Men, you may get the Pearl of Price, even from ſuch who wear the Breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of Science and Conſcience, whoſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37760:22"/>
care is (as it was ſaid of <hi>Chryſoſtom)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">In vita Chriſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Non aures titillare, ſed corda pungere;</hi> not to tickle the ears of the Hearers, but to prick and pierce their Hearts; into whoſe hearts the true Light hath ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Be diligent in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, and by frequent hearing of Sermons be ſearching for this hid Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: This is the means that God hath promiſed to bleſs when we lie with the lame man waiting at the Pool. Men <note place="margin">John 5. 3.</note> uſe to omit no opportunity to get gain; the love of Gold makes many a man not mind his meat or his ſleep, but he will toil even and take pains when he ſhould reſt, and refreſh nature; So he that would get this Jewel, muſt with the Prophets bleſſed man, <hi>meditate in the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Law of God day and night.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Such who would get skill in ſearching for <hi>Earthly Treaſures,</hi> muſt confer with others to know where the right Vein for Silver is; what tedious <note place="margin">Job 28. 1. <hi>Horace</hi> his Epiſtle.</note> Travels have been undertaken for this, <hi>Impiger extremos currit Mercator ad In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos;</hi> So ſuch as would have this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pearl muſt read and run from one <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 4. Amos 8. 12.</note> Sermon to another, inquire and retire
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37760:22"/>
into themſelves and converſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 17.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Learn from hence to prefer the Goſpel before the moſt pretious things in the world, ſince it affords a truer Pleaſure, a more induring Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Gold is got out of the baſeſt element the Earth, and admired only by men of earthy minds; who make it their God, and ſell their Souls to the Devil for it. Oh! the miſery, the miſchief that the Love of it hath wrought in the world: For this cauſe <hi>Crates</hi> the Philoſopher is ſaid to caſt his Gold into the Sea, with theſe words, <hi>Ego vos mergam, ne ipſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Solinus, c. 68.</note> 
                     <hi>mergar a vobis:</hi> It was never true to any that truſted in it. But the Goſpel though it come from <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> yet it is pure and moſt pretious, ſure and certain, eſtabliſhed for ever in Heaven: <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 89. Mat. 6. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Lay not up therefore for your ſelves a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on the Earth, where ruſt and canker do corrupt, but lay up for your ſelves a Treaſure in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But I proceed to the Pot into which this Treaſure is put; <hi>Earthen Veſſels.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37760:23"/>
                  <head>SERMON II.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>2 COR. 4. 7.</bibl>
                     <q>But we have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>WE have this <hi>Treaſure, Non pretio ſed promiſſo;</hi> not by debt but by dowry; not by purchaſe but by Promiſe. I might obſerve other things hence, but I muſt proceed.</p>
                  <p>Doct. 2. <hi>That Chriſts Embaſſadours are Earthly Veſſels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Veſſel is an Inſtrument of uſe in which we do keep or carry any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 20.</note> Commodity that concerns life's good.</p>
                  <p>And by a Metaphor it is transferred to men, who are ſo called, becauſe they are Heirs:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37760:23"/>
1. Either of Gods Election; 2. Or of his Rejection.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Of his Grace and Glory; Or 2ly. <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 21.</note> of his Anger and Indignation; For, <hi>the Potter hath power over the Clay to make one Veſſel to honour, and another to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Veſſels of Wood and ſtones, and ſuch as are hypocrites in the viſible <note place="margin">v. 22.</note> Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Veſſels of Gold and Silver, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">v. 23.</note> The Elect.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, the Word is uſed in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſignification for any one that God <note place="margin">2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 22</note> deſignes to do him ſervice in a publick or private capacity; As <hi>Cyrus, Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> &amp;c. in a ſubſerviency to his providence.</p>
                  <p>And in this ſenſe it is put for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel; and thus our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <note place="margin">Acts 9.15.</note> is called a choſen Veſſel, to bear the Name of Chriſt among the Gentiles. And they may be here called <hi>Earthly Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In reſpect of their Creation and Conſtitution, and the baſe matter of <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19. 1 Cor. 15. 47.</note> their making: <hi>Adam</hi> of <hi>Adamah,</hi> red Earth; <hi>The firſt man was of the Earth, earthly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37760:24"/>
2. In reſpect of their Corruption that cleaves to them whiles they remain in the earthly houſe of this their Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle; <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1. Acts 14. 15.</note> being ſubject to many perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and paſſions, and infirmities of fleſh and blood; you may ſee it in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 King. 15. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 17. in <hi>Jonah;</hi> in <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles: So Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in this ſenſe are <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> and Satan is ſenſible of this; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will ſift them to the bran: Can he <note place="margin">Luke 22. 31.</note> but get ſuch as they to ſide with him in the promotion of his works of darkneſs, it makes much for the advancement of his Intereſt; As <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of—a great Scholar, <hi>Cupit a te ornari Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. They are <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> in reſpect of their reſolution and diſſolution, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the ſtroke of death as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <note place="margin">Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1. 5.</note> like water ſpilt upon the ground; or like Earthen Pitchers that are carried oft to the Water, but are come broken home at laſt; <hi>Eadem conditione mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, &amp; ſimili conditione; vobiſcum, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatis afficiuntur.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Budaeus<hi>:</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. They are obnoxious to croſſes and changes in their outward eſtate in the world; they paſs from proſperity to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37760:24"/>
adverſity; they ſuffer impriſonment, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, <note place="margin">Pſal. 123: 3, 4.</note> contempt and ſcorn, and are counted the very ſcum and off-ſcouring of all things. God is pleaſed many <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 13.</note> times to empty theſe Veſſels, and to pour them forth as Wine out of a <note place="margin">Jer. 48.11.</note> Cask; and they are vilely eſteemed of men, as <hi>Veſſels</hi> of no value.</p>
                  <p>The Reaſons are ſuch as theſe:</p>
                  <p>They have here many times to do with men of earthly minds, to plant <note place="margin">Iſa. 51. 16.</note> a Heaven, and to found a Earth, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that God may do it, by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as our Tranſlators render the Words. Now what Veſſels are fitter for the Lords uſe, to call home the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 24, 25.</note> of Mercy than men like themſelves? The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would not hear of it that <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 19.</note> God ſhould ſpeak unto them immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from Heaven, but by the Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man like themſelves<hi>:</hi> So men of like paſſion, are men of more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; ſuch as can truly ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Who is weak, and I am not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>weak? Who is offended, and I burn not?</hi> Likeneſs breedeth liking, and our own weakneſs, feebleneſs, afflictions, ſtir
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37760:25"/>
up affection, as it did in <hi>Calvin;</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>He was no otherwiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards the Churches, than if he</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Beza in vit. Calv.</note> 
                     <hi>had born them upon his ſhoulders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The great Shepherd of his Sheep will have it ſo, to humble us; that when we take notice of the Treaſure we <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 7.</note> are intruſted with, we may ſeem low, and little in our own eyes, and eſteem of our ſelves <hi>Coniah,</hi> a Veſſel wherein is <note place="margin">Iſa. 13. 3. Jer. 22.28.</note> no pleaſure. Fleſh and blood is apt to boaſt in parts, in gifts, wherein happily we may eſteem to excel other men: But did we but conſider our own brittle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity, and from whom our ſufficiency comes, We would no more boaſt than of a borrowed Sute, or the Man of his Hatchet; <hi>Alas, Maſter, It was bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 6. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord doth ſo ordain, that, this precious Treaſure ſhould paſs to you through <hi>Earthen Veſſels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That you ſhould not caſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon this holy and honourable Calling of the Miniſtry, becauſe of the meanneſs of mens perſons, parts, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, trials, or temptations; ſince Gods Prophets, and even Chriſt and his Apoſtles were liable to the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37760:25"/>
                     <hi>Amos</hi> was neither a Prophet, nor the <note place="margin">Amos 1.1.</note> Son of a Prophet, but a Herd-man of <hi>Tekoah.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt before he entred upon his Miniſtry, ſerved in the mean employment of a Carpenter, his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <note place="margin">Mark 6. 3.</note> were many of them, poor Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was ſometime a Tent-maker, though indeed brought <note place="margin">Acts 18.3.</note> up at the feet of learned <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> and yet for all the trials and temptations that he indured, the <hi>Galatians</hi> were nothing the leſs indeared to him; you know, ſaith he, <hi>How that through the infirmity of the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>fleſh I preached the Goſpel, and the trials of me which was in my fleſh, ye deſpiſed not, neither abhorred.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Lord will have it ſo, that, you ſhould not have Miniſters perſons in admiration for any elegancy of Wit, <note place="margin">Jude 16.</note> excellency of Learning, ſtrength of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Since they are but Men, and of like paſſions, and the Lord is pleaſed <note place="margin">Acts 14. 15.</note> many times to hide the great myſteries <note place="margin">Mat. 11.25 1 Cor. 1. 26.</note> of his Kingdom from the wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the world; few of ſuch are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. I know well, that God diſtributes his Gifts variouſly, to ſome, a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure than to other men; and ſuch are worthy of double honour, eſpecially
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37760:26"/>
if they labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine<hi>:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 17.</note> But though you ow them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, yet you muſt not have them in admiration; For this was the Original of the various Sects at <hi>Corinth, I am of Paul, and I am of Apollos, and I of Cephas:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12.</note> and the Apoſtle is afraid, leſt any one ſhould think o him above that he ſeeth in him, and will rather glory in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 5, 6.</note> for this very cauſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Grace of <hi>regeneration</hi> may be aſcribed, not to the preaching of Men, but to the power of God; ſo in the Text, and by the operation of his Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Lords intent in this diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be to puzzle and perplex the great Wits of the world, who reſt, and relie upon their carnal wiſdom, and think thereby to fathom the depth of theſe <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 18.</note> Myſteries; but ſuch muſt empty their Veſſels of this Earthly Treaſure, and count it traſh, before they be capable of <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 7.</note> conceiving of, or receiving in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Wiſdom and Knowledg in Chriſt; for, <hi>Intus exiſtens prohibet alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num;</hi> If any man among you ſeem to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 18, 19.</note> that he may be wiſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:37760:26"/>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Admire the goodneſs and gracious condeſcention of God, who might have delivered his mind to you by the miniſtration of Angels, and in terrible things; as at the Tradition of the Law upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> with <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 18.</note> thunder, lightning, and ſound of a Trumpet, the Mountain burning, and covered with blackneſs, darkneſs <note place="margin">Heb. 12.18.</note> and tempeſt, ſo full of terror, that, not only the People, but, even <hi>Moſes</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <note place="margin">Exod. 19. 16.</note> trembled: But God was pleaſed to deliver his will to you, by men formed of the ſame clay, cut out of the ſame <note place="margin">Job 33.6, 7.</note> lump with your ſelves, <hi>Earthen Veſſels.</hi> Well may we ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Lord, What is man,</hi> ſorry, ſickly, mortal, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 4.</note> man, <hi>that thou ſhouldſt be thus mindful of him?</hi> to leave thy mind to us, and <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 1.</note> deliver it by the Miniſtry of Men, As the Diſciples ſaid!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. If the Apoſtle who was ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent an Inſtrument of Chriſt, and laboured more abundantly than the reſt; <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 10.</note> yet makes himſelf equal with others, as an <hi>Earthen Veſſel;</hi> nay, in ſome ſenſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, the leaſt of Saints, the laſt of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, How doth this reprehend the <note place="margin">Eph. 3.8.</note> Pride of the Pope, who takes to him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37760:27"/>
the moſt magnificent Titles, ſuch as no meer man, without the higheſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy may arrogate to himſelf; ſuch as that Paſtor of the Catholick Church, which he blaſphemouſly calleth his own <note place="margin">Ceremon. b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ſect. 2. 2 Theſ. 2.3 Bellarm. de Sum. Pont. l. 2. 23.</note> Spouſe; nay, arrogates to himſelf the Title of God, and ſets himſelf above Princes who are petty gods, and ſo proves himſelf to be the Antichriſt: and though he pretends his power from <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> yet follows not his Precepts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 3. and aſſimilates him in nothing, except in denying his Maſter.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What an excellent patern of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity have we here, who are the Paſtors of Chriſt's Flock, not to lord it over <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note> them, but to allure them by love; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 2.</note> meekneſs to all men, and inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves to be very <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 25.</note> tender of them, and apt to compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them in their ſorrows and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſince we are of the like frailty our ſelves! This ſhould make us ſay with <hi>Moſes, Who am I?</hi> If there be any Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Treaſure in us, it is Chriſts Gift, he gave it, and let him have the glory of it; <hi>Not I, but the Grace of God which is</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>in me.</hi> The more any man beholds the Suns body, the leſs he ſees, when he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37760:27"/>
looks to the Earth; So we beholding the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould aſcribe the excellency of the power to God, and not to our <note place="margin">Pſal. 115. 1.</note> ſelves; <hi>Non nobis Domine, non nobis; ſed nomini tuo da gloriam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. You ſhould not value the Goſpel the leſs vertually, but rather have it in the greater veneration, becauſe it comes to you in or through <hi>Earthen Veſſels.</hi> We are very apt, naturally, to look at the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance of things or perſons, and accordingly to prize and prefer them. For this St. <hi>James</hi> taxeth his Hearers, who in their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies had reſpect to him that had on a Gold Ring, and gay cloathing<hi>:</hi> So or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily, <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 3.</note> men ſhew eſteem to ſuch things that are gorgeous and glorious in the eye of the world, and to ſuch Men, ſuch Miniſters, as ſhew forth in their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons much humane Learning and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; and in the mean time, neglect, and ſlight the godly ſimplicity of the Goſpel, and ſuch as preach it in the power of the Holy-Ghoſt; This is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality in the Apoſtles account: Not that I ſpeak againſt Learning, which is an excellent Hand-maid to Divinity;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37760:28"/>
but the abuſe of it when men darken the Truth through the miſts of Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſpeculations, and preach, <hi>Magis ut</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2. 8. St. <hi>Aug.</hi> Multi propter arborem ſcientiae amittunt arborem vitae.</note> 
                     <hi>placerent, quam docerent;</hi> to pleaſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to profit. If men ſet ſuch a price upon Earthly Treaſures; digged out of the bowels of the Earth, and delivered with dirty hands; How much more ſhould you value the Goſpel though it come from Inſtruments that are <hi>Earthen Veſſels?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſerve the Exhortation of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>We beſeech you, Brethren, know them</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 5. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>that labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, and have them in ſingular love, for their works ſake.</hi> Though there be no worthineſs in the perſon, yet, it is a worthy work, it is high and honourable, divine and heavenly; the preparation to it, the execution of it is ſo, if you conſider <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 1</note> the worth of a precious ſoul, by the price that was payed to purchaſe it; not Gold nor Silver, but the pretious Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Reward that <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 18, 18.</note> will be given to ſuch as are Inſtrumental in the work; the ſaving a ſoul from death, and the hiding a multitude of ſins; and how mean ſoever they appear <note place="margin">Jam. 5.20.</note>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:37760:28"/>
in the Fleſh, yet hereafter they ſhall ſhine as the Stars in the Kingdom of their Father for evermore. <note place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Admire the depth of Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in this; That the Lord ſhould make uſe of our weakneſs and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, for the manifeſtation of his mighty Power in bringing ſinners from Satans Kingdom, and their ſinful courſes, to accept of Salvation through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Well may the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſtle ſay, <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>things?</hi> We are not ſufficient of our ſelves to conceive, to perceive, what is our Duty, what is the Dignity of the <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> Miniſtry, much leſs the depth of the Myſteries of Salvation, we are to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence<hi>:</hi> Our ſufficiency, and your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, is of God; we are poor, frail, Earthen Pitchers, appointed by God, to bear this precious Treaſure; if he blow upon us, How ſoon ſhall we become broken Pot-ſheards? <hi>Who am I</hi> (ſaith) meek <hi>Moſes?</hi> And <hi>who am I,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 18. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>and what is my life</hi> (ſaith) holy <hi>David?</hi> So who am I? and what is my life? a breath, a bubble, a vapor; How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to bear a Pitcher, a Lamp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Pitcher! To blow the Trumpet, <note place="margin">Judg. 7. 16</note>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37760:29"/>
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58, 1. To ſay, not (as they) for the Lord, and for <hi>Gideon;</hi> but for the Lord, and for Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Oh the depth</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 33.</note> 
                     <hi>both of the wiſdom and knowledg of God!</hi> Here is a depth indeed, wherein a man might dwell. As <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> diſcourſing about the Love of God in Chriſt, ſaith, Oh I am like a man digging in a deep Spring; I ſtand here, and the water riſeth upon me, and there, and ſtill it riſeth upon me: We are not of Gods Cabinet Counſel; we have not <hi>David</hi>'s Key to open this Secret, and it is not ſafe to be prying into this Ark; <hi>Mirari</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 7. Mallem ignorare ſine cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine quam ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <hi>Eucli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>potius quàm rimari, ſapientia noſtra.</hi> Let us admire, what we cannot underſtand; only this, What cannot God do, that is not ſinful, if it pleaſe him? who makes his Power appear in our weakneſs, and gives you this <hi>Treaſure in Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6. Endeavour to do all the good you can by, and to receive all the good, that is tendered you in the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, ſince your Miniſters are frail, mortal Creatures, <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> that will ſoon be broken.</p>
                  <p>It will not be long before a period be
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37760:29"/>
put to my preaching, your hearing; to all our prayers, repentance and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for death, and for judgment; there will be no longer pardon tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or graces to be attained; <hi>no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, no wiſdom in the grave whither we</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.7, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>are going.</hi> There will be no Accounts caſt up, no Counſel given or taken; no doing of work, but a receiving of wages, according to our work done. <hi>Work</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 9. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>therefore while it is day;</hi> whiles you have life, and light, and health, and ſtrength, and time and talents; before dim eyes, and ſailing hands, and feeble feet, and ſainting hearts, through the infirmities of old age, come upon you. You are called Labourers, and muſt not loyter; Souldiers, and muſt fight; ſea-faring Men, and muſt hoiſe up Sails, whiles the wind ſits; Husbandmen, and muſt plow up your fallow ground; Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, and muſt give an account<hi>:</hi> You have your task ſet, and have played the truants too long already; and if you do not haſten, you will hardly have done your work before the Lord comes; <hi>Therefore while it is called to day barden not your hearts.</hi> Be not like little children that conſume their Candle in play and <note place="margin">Pſal. 95.8. Heb. 3.8.</note>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:37760:30"/>
ſport, and are forced to go to bed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the dark.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Now ſince both the Text and the Time, leads me to it, I cannot but take notice of two Occurences of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence that have hapned to the Inhabitants of this Pariſh and to my ſelf, as concerned herein this preſent Month of <hi>April.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt was the Lords gracious goodneſs, and the Kings Royal Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in reſtoring me to my Miniſtry at this place, who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> before civilly dead; and here I have continued a year com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, with the love, &amp; good liking of my He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ers (not without the oppoſition and contradiction of ſome who are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious at my preaching, and caſt contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies upon my perſon) but none of <note place="margin">Acts 20. 23, 24.</note> theſe things move me, <hi>Homo ſum, nihil haec à me aliena puto;</hi> Only the fruits of the affliction, and the ſucceſs of my ſervice; Oh that I could ſee more of this! that I might not complain of running in vain; nor you of dry breſts, or a miſcarrying womb. My preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I well know, hath been in much weakneſs, and in fear and trembling; <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.3.</note>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37760:30"/>
For, as that grave Father told <hi>Libanius</hi> the Rhetorician, <hi>Non Oratorum filii ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed Piſcatorum;</hi> we are not the ſons of Orators, but of Fiſhermen. It is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient excuſe, to ſay what you have heard, came to you through an <hi>Earthen Veſſel;</hi> and therefore pray unto God who made mans mouth, the dumb to ſpeak, and the blind to ſee, that he would cauſe this light to ſhine out of darkneſs into your hearts; that ſo the excellency of the power may appear to be of God, and not of Man.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſecond Occurrence; this Month is likewiſe memorable, for the Death of Reverend Mr. <hi>Hall,</hi> ſome-time a Preacher in this Place, but a faithful Paſtor in the Pariſh where he ſerved (as he ſaid) a double Apprenticeſhip; of whom, though I have ſaid ſomething heretofore, yet I can never ſay enough. His Life was a Tranſcript of his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and his Soul was ſtored with a Treaſure of many Divine Graces and Gifts which he hid not in a Napkin, or put under a Buſhel, but expended for the publick good: Yet having this Treaſure in an <hi>Earthen Veſſel,</hi> the Lamp of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37760:31"/>
his Life went out by enlightening o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; yet without waſte; for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of this Ointment hath yielded a ſweet perfume in the CHURCH of GOD.</p>
                  <trailer>The End of the Second Sermon.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <head>His CHARACTER.</head>
                  <p>HE was a man of middle Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his Hair blackiſh, which he wore very ſhort, ſcarce to cover his ears; his Face pale, and ſomewhat long; his Spirit brisk and lively, active and able to bear the brunt of buſineſs; and was ſeldom or never known to be caſt down with diſcouragements, though often mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and impriſoned by Souldiers, and peſtered with Sectaries of all ſorts: His Eyes were ſparkling, eſpecially when he was intent upon the delivery of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of worth and weight: The cloaths he wore, were rather coarſe than coſtly; his carriage and behaviour, courteous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37760:31"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd attractive; his temper and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ution inclined him to choler, and he would break out ſometimes into paſſion; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut would ſoon recal himſelf, and that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or the future, he might not ſin in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nger, he would reſolve to be angry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or nothing but Sin. One thing hath been obſerved in him, he would be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-credulous, ſay ſome, in receiving Reports upon truſt, without examining the Truth of what was told him, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when it came from ſuch as he had a good opinion of for Godlineſs; which I impute not ſo much to his weakneſs, as to the ſincerity and ſimple plainneſs of his own heart, his own words being the iſſues of his upright heart, he judged ſo of other men. For his judgment (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was in the matters of the world) yet doubtleſs it was deep in the ſearch, and diſcovery of the Myſteries of the Goſpel and of Godlineſs; which he got by frequent Communion with God, and walking in his fear all the day long, <hi>and the ſecret of the Lord is with ſuch as</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal, 25. 14</note> 
                     <hi>fear him.</hi> He could ſee more in theſe ſacred Riddles by Prayer, than by his Learning, and much labour in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37760:32"/>
For his Judgment about Diſcipline, he was of the Presbyterian Perſwaſion; and happily <hi>he was</hi> held too rigid by his Brethren, that diſſented from him in this<hi>:</hi> and though more more mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and moderation was deſirable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially towards Diſſenters, who ſerve the ſame God, and ſeek jointly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt, in the power and purity of his Ordinances; yet doubtleſs what he did, was out of a zeal for the Truth, which he took this to be. And to my knowledg he <note place="margin">I can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he gave a Legacy at his death to one who was of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary judgment to him in Diſcipline and Church-Order.</note> had a Catholick Charity for all ſuch in whoſe hearts he perceived the Seed of true Grace to be ſown, though they differed far from him in Judgment<hi>:</hi> for his love to the Saints, was not grounded upon an identity of Opinion, but on a ſweet ſuitableneſs and harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſneſs in Grace; and whoever he found to have in him <hi>aliquid Chriſti,</hi> was the Object of his Love<hi>:</hi> and though he had a hatred towards the ſins of all (were they never ſo great in place), yet, not to their perſons, which he would pity and pray for, and reprove<hi>:</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37760:32"/>
And as he was jealous over this houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of God, with godly jealouſie; ſo <note place="margin">Prov. 4.23.</note> in particular, over his own heart, which he kept above all other keepings with much Chriſtian caution; well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that, if the Spring were clear, the ſtreams would ſoon clear themſelves; and leſt the fleſh ſhould wax wanton, and kick, he would keep it down by ſevere mortification and abſtinence, giving himſelf much to private prayer and faſting. Indeed he was at all times temperate in the uſe of the Creature; even at Feaſts he would feed very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly upon a few Diſhes, and would commonly riſe from the Table before others had half-dined. But of all other things, he was moſt ſpare of his time, which he eſteemed a choice Treaſure, and the loſs of it irreparable; and what ſhreds of it he could ſcrape together from a double publick imployment he had, he ſpent in writing Books<hi>:</hi> In compoſing of which, he ſtudied very hard &amp; ſate up late; for he had this happineſs above many other men (as he ſaid), he found himſelf beſt when he was moſt ſtrongly employed; his Work was to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37760:33"/>
him inſtead of Phyſick, and he choſe rather to ſpend himſelf in Labour, than to conſume with ruſt and ſickneſs. See more in his following Life.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ABEL REDIVIV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> OR THE DEAD SPEAKER.</p>
                  <p>The Subſtance of an Anniverſary SERMON, Preached at <hi>Withall, April</hi> 26. 1674.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is annexed certain dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Speeches of many Modern DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINES, eſpecially of Mr. <hi>THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS HALL,</hi> late Paſtor of <hi>Kings-Norton.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>HEB. 11. 4.</bibl> 
                     <hi>And by it he, being Dead, yet ſpeaketh.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and three <hi>Crowns,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1674.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To my much eſteemed Friend, Mr.</hi> William Turton <hi>of</hi> Aulderways <hi>in</hi> Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Worthy Sir;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> may wonder at my boldneſs, in preſuming to prepoſe your Name to this popular Sermon, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect draught of the Life and Death of Mr. <hi>HALL,</hi> who may ſeem a ſtranger to you: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I do not remember that I ſaw your Face, ſince the time, that the Lord (who ſets the bounds of our habitations) had caſt our Lot toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a pleaſant place, in a time of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s troubles; where we only heard the Voice of Chriſts Turtle-Dove, and had not thoſe dreadful
<pb facs="tcp:37760:35"/>
Allarums of War, under which other parts of the Kingdom trembled, and the very pillars of it tottered.</p>
                  <p>That which now encourageth me to this Attempt, is, that I took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of your conſtant attendance upon the Ordinances of Chriſt, and your readineſs to ſympathize with the ſufferings of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the reſpect you had to the godly Paſtors of the Church; in particular to the perſon ſpoken of in the enſuing Narrative, betwixt whom and your ſelf, it is ſaid, there was a near alliance; but doubtleſs, there was an intimate friendſhip and aloſe familiarity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; the remembrance of which, I hope, ſtill liveth in your heart, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily no leſs than <hi>Jonathans</hi> did in the breaſt of <hi>Davids,</hi> or <hi>Baſils</hi> in <hi>Nazianzens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As therefore <hi>Epaminondas</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the body of his faſt Friend <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                     <hi>Pelopidas,</hi> whom he ſuppoſed was ſlain and ſaw lying upon a heap of
<pb facs="tcp:37760:35"/>
dead men: ſo I ſuppoſed you would be ready to defend this poor Piece written concerning your deceaſed Friend, of whom, though I have ſaid ſomewhat, yet not the one half that I might. Tou would not think me to be partial, ſhould I ſay of him what <hi>Nazianzen</hi> did of <hi>Baſil</hi> aforeſaid; <hi>Antiqua probitate, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitate<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> praeditus &amp; eruditis pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, &amp; piis erudition is laude ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellens;</hi> Some that were more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Learning, he excelled in Piety; and ſome that were more <note place="margin">
                        <hi>See Mr.</hi> Leys <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to his Com. up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 2 Tim. <hi>as alſo Mr.</hi> Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my<hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle.</hi>
                     </note> famous for Piety, he excelled in Learning: And indeed, he was held to be by ſuch as well knew him, and were able to judg of mens parts and piety, both learned and religious.</p>
                  <p>I have no more to ſay concerning him in this place; I only beg your pardon and Patronage, together with a ſhare in your prayers, that what is ſaid in the enſuing Leaves, may
<pb facs="tcp:37760:36"/>
find acceptance with God, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the eyes of his people.</p>
                  <p>And my earneſt deſire and prayer to <hi>God</hi> for you, is, that he who holdeth your ſoul in life, and hath lined it out to or beyond <hi>David</hi>'s ſpan, would give you much joy and peace in believing; That whilſt your Body is deſcending towards the <hi>Common Mother</hi> the Earth, your Soul may aſcend as towards the top of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> to deſcry the Holy Land; that the nearer you come to the pit of corruption, the more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared you may be for that place of perfection; <hi>and like a Tree plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Courts of Gods Houſe, you may bring forth Fruit even in old Age;</hi> This, <hi>(I</hi> ſay) <hi>Sir,</hi> ſhall be the prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Servant in our deareſt Saviour and Redeemer, <hi>Richard Moore.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="3" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37760:36"/>
                  <head>SERMON III.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>HEB. 11. 4.</bibl>
                     <q>And by it he, being dead, yet ſpeaketh.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>IN the former Chapter the Apoſtle preſſeth the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Faith; and here in this, by a Digreſſion, he demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates the nature of this Grace, from the Effects.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You have the Myſteries that it contains.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Hiſtories that hold it forth.</p>
                  <p>1. The effects that declare the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Faith are three.</p>
                  <p>1. It begets a ſure and certain Hope of the accompliſhment of Gods Promiſes.<note place="margin">v. 1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the ſubſtance of them: though the thing promiſed have no preſent exiſtence or being, yet Faith makes them obvious and evident to the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; for it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the ground or confidence by putting that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37760:37"/>
which is hoped for, as if we had it in hand, and things inviſible for ſuch as are conceived by ſenſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Effect of Faith is drawn from a demonſtration of the Elders, that by it received an excellent Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial that they pleaſed God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and were bleſſed partakers of the benefits of the<note place="margin">v. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Meſſias</hi> only by believing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A third Fruit of Faith is, that by it we underſtand things incredible to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as the Creation of the World, which<note place="margin">v. 3.</note> was formed and faſhioned by the Word of God, without appearance of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſting matter; yet hereby having reſpect to Gods Omnipotency, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it that ſo it was.</p>
                  <p>And this is inſtanced and exemplified in the following Cloud of Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>1. Of ſuch as lived before. 2. In ſuch as were after the Floud.</p>
                  <p>The firſt ſort of Witneſſes were, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> here in my Text; <note place="margin">v. 5.7.</note> who was the <hi>Proto-Martyr</hi> of the world, as <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt Murtherer. <hi>Adam</hi> indeed ſlew all his Poſterity, in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe; but <hi>Cain</hi> his Brother bodily and bloodily: And as <hi>Adam</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Parent of mankind, was deceived
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37760:37"/>
in the Fruit of Paradiſe<hi>:</hi> So here he, and eſpecially <hi>Eve</hi> was in the Fruit of <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 1. c. 3. 15.</note> the Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>For though the name <hi>Cain</hi> ſignifieth a Poſſeſſion, and notwithſtanding he built a City; yet was he of the wicked One, and was no Heir of that City, <hi>whoſe Builder and Maker was God:</hi> And his Mother ſenſible of the deception in <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 2.</note> the Firſt-born when ſhe brought forth the ſecond Son, gave him a name ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hereunto; for the Word <hi>Abel</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Letter <hi>Aleph,</hi> imports mourning; but with <hi>He,</hi> Vanity, one <note place="margin">Joſephus Antiq. b. 1. c. 2.</note> humbled in mind, and holding ſuch Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions Vanity.</p>
                  <p>Here then you have two Men the only Heirs of the World offering Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God with different Succeſs<hi>:</hi> For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Abel</hi>'s Offering was more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table than <hi>Cain</hi>'s.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Cauſe of this; not in reſpect of Sacrifice it ſelf or the matter of it; for the Fruit of the ground might have pleaſed God, as well as the Firſtlings of the Flock; but it was Faith that made the difference.</p>
                  <p>1. God had reſpect to <hi>Abels</hi> perſon
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37760:38"/>
juſtified by Faith, and ſo to his perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 4.</note> and to his Sacrifice as a Fruit of his Faith; teſtifying of his Gifts, by <note place="margin">Levit. 9. 24.</note> ſome token of his favour and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Faith, probably by Fire fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">Judg. 6. 21.</note> upon the Sacrifice; but he had not ſo to <hi>Cains,</hi> which was all the ground <note place="margin">1 King. 18. 3.</note> of the grudge he had againſt him.</p>
                  <p>This Faith of <hi>Abels</hi> is further illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By the Evidence of it; he obtained witneſs that he was righteous.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By the recompence of it; he was rewarded and regarded of God by his Faith; the Lord took care of him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Text.</note> his Death, reputed him among his Saints, whoſe death is precious in his ſight; His Blood cried to God, and <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 14 Gen. 4. 10.</note> the ground that received it, uttered a Voice, and was clamorous againſt the Murderer; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>by it he, being dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> or rather, as the Learned Criticks tranſlate it, is yet ſpoken of, <hi>Nempe in Scriptura,</hi> ſaith <hi>Beza.</hi> Where-ever <hi>Abels</hi> Faith is ſpoken of, whether in the Scripture, or preached of and publiſhed to the world, though ſince he were dead; yet ſtill there ſhall be a memorial of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37760:38"/>
him, as if he were yet alive, as was ſaid of that Woman in the Goſpel by our Lord and Saviour, <hi>Where-ever this Goſpel ſhall be preached in the whole world,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 26.13</note> 
                     <hi>there ſhall alſo this, that this woman hath done, be told for a memorial of her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doct. <hi>That the renowned fame of the Saints, who lived by, and died in the Faith, ſhall be recorded as well as recompenced and rewarded after their death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.6</note> 
                     <hi>remembrance;</hi> their good name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown ſhall not only be laſting when they ſhall be laid aſleep in the duſt, but it ſhall be for an everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> makes out the proof of this, by Contraries; <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria juxta ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt: The memory of the juſt is bleſſed, and the Name of the wicked ſhall not.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 10.7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abels</hi> Sacrifice ſhall have a ſavour of acceptance <hi>Maries</hi> Ointment ſhall ſmell ſweet in the Noſtrils of God and good Men, and <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſhall have a <note place="margin">John 3.</note> good report of all, and even of the Truth it ſelf. When <hi>Cains</hi> Murder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Judas</hi> his monſtrous Treaſon, and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoloms</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:37760:39"/>
Rebellion ſhall be an everlaſting abomination. See for the further open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Point.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What it is to live by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt?</item>
                     <item>2. Who they are that do ſo?</item>
                     <item>3. How a Believer is ſaid to ſpeak not only living but dead?</item>
                     <item>4. Why a Saint is ſaid ſo to do?</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. The juſt man is ſaid to live by his Faith. <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 4.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> dead by the Law, revived by the Goſpel; from the time of his Converſion to the time of his Diſſolution; whilſt he abode in the body of Fleſh, <hi>he lived by the Faith of the Son of God;</hi> and being dead, yet <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 2.</note> ſpeaketh in the lively Oracles of the Word of Life.</p>
                  <p>In alluſion to this ſpeech of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; <hi>Behold!</hi> (ſaith Reverend Dr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet,</hi> upon his Death bed) <hi>I am dead, I am riſen again; I live no more in my ſelf, but I live in the life of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. To live by Faith is to ſeed upon a <note place="margin">Hab. 3. 17.</note> Promiſe, in the failure of outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and to draw out from thence
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37760:39"/>
ſupports and ſupplies to bear up the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 38. 11. 38.</note> of life in a Believer. When there is no viſible appearance in the Creature, no bloſſom on the Fig-tree, nor fruit in the Vine, then Chriſt muſt be the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians life, breath and bread; he will intereſt himſelf in a Promiſe of the Word, as his preſent portion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, <note place="margin">Heb. 11.39</note> though he have not yet recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the things promiſed in hand, but only hath it in hope.</p>
                  <p>And were we to paſs ſentence who is a rich Man, we would not ſo much look into his Purſe to ſee how much Gold he hath, but into his Cheſt to ſee what Deeds and Indentures, what Bonds and Evidences he hath: So if you would ſee whether you are Rich and Righteous towards God, be ſure ſearch what Promiſes you have treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in your hearts; For as he is a rich Man who is rich in Bonds; ſo the Believer that can plead the Promiſe in prayer and put theſe Bonds in ſute.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As the true Believer lives to God, ſo he hath laid up for him a goodly he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage; and though for the preſent he be but as the Heir under age, yet he is <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.6. Gal. 4. 1.</note> ſealed with the holy Spirit of Promiſe,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37760:40"/>
which is the Earneſt of the Inheritance <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 14.</note> until the Redemption of the purchaſed Poſſeſſion. Every Believer is an Heir of God, and a joint-heir with Chriſt, and <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 17</note> hath an aſſurance of the heavenly Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance here: 1. By Purchaſe. 2. By Promiſe. 3. And in the firſt-fruits of the Spirit, which is a part of the whole, as an Earneſt is a part of payment for the Purchaſe.</p>
                  <p>3. A Believer is ſaid to ſpeak not only living but dead; 1. By his Blood. 2. By his Example. 3. By his Precept.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By his Blood; And in this ſenſe the Blood of Chriſt is ſaid to ſpeak <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things than the blood of Abel:</hi> it <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 24</note> ſpeaks peace, pardon, remiſſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God; but the Blood <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 10.</note> of <hi>Abel</hi> cries and calleth for puniſhment, revenge and vengeance.</p>
                  <p>The glorified Saints cannot be ſaid <note place="margin">Rev. 6. 10. Rom. 12. 19.</note> thus to ſpeak properly; they ſeek not revenge, but leave it to God, whoſe Prerogative it is; it is meant only of the provocation of their ſuffering.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Believers may be ſaid to ſpeak by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir Example for the worlds imitation and admonition; not only living but <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 6, 11. Jam. 5.10.</note> dead. So the Apoſtle, <hi>Take my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37760:40"/>
                     <hi>the Prophets for an enſample in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, who have ſpoken to you in the Name of the Lord. The Prophets were now dead.</hi> yet they had left ſuch renowned Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and Examples of Patience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, that they even ſpeak yet to us by their heroick and impregnable Faith and Fortitude, in bearing inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and forbearing enemies, in taking patiently the ſpoiling of their Goods, knowing this, that they had in Heaven <hi>a more induring ſubſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Believers may be ſaid to ſpeak, not only living and dying, but even when dead, by the lively Precepts they left behind, after they went off the ſtage of this world, and were buried with their Fathers. thus they are ſaid to ſpeak with us at this very day.</p>
                  <p>Faith hath this mighty force and efficacy in it, that it works won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <note place="margin">Iſa. 26. 19.</note> in Heaven and Earth, and in the Grave; by virtue of it many received <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 35.</note> their dead to life again; as the Widow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> the <hi>Sbunamite,</hi> and the Friends of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> Faith hath a force to remove Mountains, and true juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith is not beneath Miracles. Jeſus
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37760:41"/>
Chriſt is the Prince and Principle of Life, and his People are the only Heirs together of the Grace of Life, and all <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 7.</note> ſuch as believe in him, though they were dead, yet ſhall they live; nay, <note place="margin">John 11. 25, 26.</note> they ſhall never die; and if they ſhall never die, they ſhall ever ſpeak; for Life is the Principle of Speech. I ſhall not need to tell you how great things have been done this way by Art, if we might believe what is ſaid in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Mnemons</hi> Statue, recorded by <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mnemonis</hi> Saxea Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figies vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> 
                     <hi>Tacitus.</hi> It is ſufficient what we receive here from the Divine Oracles of the Word. <hi>Abel</hi> here, though dead ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years ago, yet his Faith makes him a ſpeaking Doctor to the Church, even to this day. Learn by his Example how to make all your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Duties and Services acceptable to God, even by mixing them with Faith in the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Your Prayers will never prevail at the Throne of Grace, if you do <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 22.</note> not ask in Faith.</item>
                     <item>2. You cannot profit by the Word preached, except you mix it with <note place="margin">Heb. 4.2.</note> Faith in your hearts.</item>
                     <item>3. The Sacramen is received without <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:37760:41"/>
Faith are unfruitful. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was uſed to call upon thoſe that went to the Lords Table, <hi>Non parare fauces ſed fidem;</hi> Not to ſharpen their Teeth, but to quicken their Faith.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. It ſerves to ſhew forth the miſerable ſtate of all ſuch who live after the fleſh, and not by the Faith of the Son of God; ſuch indeed are dead whilſt they live, and are deteſtable when dead<hi>:</hi> they live undeſired, and die unlamented; and as their ſenſual <note place="margin">Gen. 16.4.</note> lives did beſpeak them bruitiſh; ſo their death ſhall be abominable, and their <note place="margin">Pſal. 9. 6.</note> memorial periſh with them, as that of the Beaſts: and as their life was not worth a prayer, ſo their death ſhall not be worthy of a tear: As was ſaid of <hi>Jehoiakim, None ſhall take up a lamentation for them, ſaying, Ah, my Brother, or ah,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 22. 18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>my Siſter; ah, Lord, or ah, his Glory; but they ſhall be buried with the burial of an Aſs;</hi> and if there be any mention at all made of them, it is in contempt and deteſtation. Lo, this is the man, now the Monſter to be pointed at; once ſo <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.4.</note> mighty, now ſo miſerable; that made not God his ſtrength, but truſted in the<note place="margin">v. 7.</note>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:37760:42"/>
abundance of his riches, and ſtrengthened himſelf in his wickedneſs.</p>
                  <p>Oh! that ſuch would conſider this, who are ſenſual in their lives, and who feaſt themſelves without fear, and make it their main care to cater for their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes, or to lay up for themſelves trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon the Earth, and to build ſtately Tombs to be a memorial of them when they are dead. Alas, theſe Sepulchres will be opened, and your rottenneſs will be diſcovered before God, Angels and Men; not ſo much by the ſhew of your Countenances, as by the light of your Conſciences: the guilt of which you will be no more able to abide or avoid, than <hi>Cain</hi> was the Cry of his brothers <note place="margin">Gen. 4.10, 14.</note> blood.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As you deſire to leave a renowned Fame behind you in the places where you live, and a ſweet perfume to your Names when you die; live much by Faith in this life. The Lord reckoneth of our life, by our belief; and ſo much we are ſaid to live to God, as we believe in Chriſt, and no more, when we relie upon him in the uſe of lawful means, or in the want of Creature-comforts. <note place="margin">Hab. 3.17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh! that the blind and bruitiſh
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37760:42"/>
world were convinced once of the truth of this, who are apt to think that they live by their Lands, and by their Labours in their lawful Callings, and will truſt God no further than they have his preſent pawn.</p>
                  <p>Oh! that the profane and unclean crew who live as they liſt, after their own wills, and ways and works, in the luſts of the fleſh, and in the pleaſures of ſin, would but be perſwaded that they are dead even whiles they live; as the prodigal and her that lived in pleaſure, <note place="margin">Luke 15. 24.</note> are ſaid to be.</p>
                  <p>The debauched Adulterer and your ſwiniſh ſwiller are deceived by Satan, to believe they have the fineſt life of it, becauſe they know no better. Were you but once brought over to Jeſus Chriſt by believing, you would never deſire to turn again to your former vomit. Ah, How could you be without theſe bitter ſweets, that have a ſting in the tail of them!</p>
                  <p>You that live by your wits, and make no conſcience of cozening and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in your Calling, in your buying and ſelling, lending or borrowing; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, if you were once acquainted what
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37760:43"/>
it is to live by Faith, how contentedly would you acquieſce under Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential diſpenſations, without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or ſeeking after unlawful means!</p>
                  <p>A Believer will live upon God when he hath nothing elſe to ſubſiſt by; and believe him upon his bare word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, without ſight of preſent provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. If there be but a little Meal in the Barrel, and a little Oyl in the Cruiſe, when he hath only the gleaning of the Vintage, here and there a Cluſter upon the upeprmoſt boughs or branches; nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when the Figtree bloſſometh not, nor the Vine doth not yield her fruit, and the labour of the Olive fail, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For this <hi>Abraham</hi> was honoured with God and Man; he for this cauſe was called, <hi>The Father of the Faithful.</hi> The <note place="margin">Gen. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>Hittites</hi> counted him a Prince of God and <hi>Jacob</hi> likewiſe was one that had princely power with God; and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour <note place="margin">Mat. 8. 10.</note> not only admires and wonders at, but even commends the Faith of the Centurion, and that of the Woman o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Canaan;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh woman, Great is thy Faith</hi> Theſe and many more that's mentioned in the Goſpel, and in particular in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chapter, whence I take my Text, leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37760:43"/>
a good report behind them in that they lived by Faith.</p>
                  <p>Faith is as a ſweet ſavour that refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Soul in which it is ſeated, more than Musk or Civet do the ſenſes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the ſtench of evil courſes and companies<hi>:</hi> It is as a ſweet ſmell to ſuch as live by it in the midſt of walking dunghils; it chears up the mind in the midſt of diſcouragements, and clears the Conſcience and comforts it; and makes men as merry as the Martyrs were under their Bonds; it even fatteneth the bones<hi>:</hi> Upon this account <hi>Demetrius</hi> had a good report of all men, and of the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 30. 3 Joh. 12.</note> Truth it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fabrianus</hi> the Martyr ſaid, firſt bitter and then ſweet; firſt battel and then victory; every drop of my blood ſhall preach Chriſt and ſet forth his praiſe.</p>
                  <p>I know (ſaith Mr. <hi>Bilny)</hi> by Senſe, and Philoſophy, That Fire is hot and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is painful; but by Faith, that it ſhall only waſte the ſtubble of my body, and purge my Spirit of its corruption.</p>
                  <p>One ſeeing a weak woman go chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to priſon, ſaid; Oh you have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taſted the bitterneſs of death<hi>: No,</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>nor never ſhall; For Chriſt bath</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:37760:44"/>
                     <hi>promiſed, that they that keep his ſayings ſhall never ſee death.</hi> A Believer may feel the ſtroke, but not the ſting of death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignatius</hi> going to ſuffer Martyrdom, triumphed in this, that his blood ſhould be found among the mighty Worthies; and that the Lord when he maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition for blood, will recount from the blood of righteous <hi>Abel;</hi> not only to the blood of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> but alſo to the blood of mean <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was a ſweet ſaying of holy Mr. <hi>Hall</hi> in time of his health; That the ſweet reſcent of a well-ſpent life, would be matter of ſingular comfort, at a dying day.</p>
                  <p>He would have his Hearers, learn to know, and know to do; do to die, and die to live.</p>
                  <p>In his ſickneſs, he ſaid, I am now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where I ſhall have reſt from Sin, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and from all fear, wearineſs, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and from all the evils and errours of a wicked world; for <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Job 19. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>the laſt day upon the earth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Oh let my life be nothing but prayer and praiſes, ſince God had dealt bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37760:44"/>
with me! and even whiles he was breathing out his laſt breath, he ſpake thus; <hi>All the joys of this life are nothing; nothing to the joys that are in Jeſus Chriſt, Come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though he be now dead, yet he ſpeaks to you, not by his Words, but by his Works; by Precept and by Preſident. Oh labour to lead his life, that you may die his death; for if you tread in the footſteps of his Faith, though death bring your body to Corruption, yet ſhall it never bring your ſouls to Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>I am now cloſing up the ſecond year of my Miniſtry among you; And Lord, what have I been doing here all this while, that ſo few of this Congregation have been brought from death to life, to embrace Chriſt by Faith, and to lead a holy life, and to live to him? Shall I ſay with the Prophet, I have ſpent my ſtrength in vain, and laboured for a thing of nought? I hope better things of you; and I am perſwaded better of ſome of you, and that I may the better prevail with you to live by Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member who it is that ſpeaketh to you,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37760:45"/>
                     <hi>viz.</hi> one that is eſteemed as dead, And will you not credit ſuch a Witneſs?</p>
                  <p>It was the requeſt of <hi>Dives</hi> to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 30, 31.</note> that dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> might be ſent unto his five Brethren; he thought that if one came to them from the dead, they would believe and repent.</p>
                  <p>Such a ſight or report indeed might work upon the fancy; but it is the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel preached that muſt work upon the affections<hi>:</hi> For my own part, I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Truth of the Goſpel upon ſurer Grounds and upon better Authority, than if I had received it from one raiſed from the dead.</p>
                  <p>For ſuch a Teſtimony, if it be only Humane, can beget but a humane Faith; and ſhould it be more than this, we might ſee cauſe to queſtion whether it were Divine or Diabolical; for even Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan can transform himſelf into an Angel of Light. Therefore be building up your ſelves daily in your holy Faith, by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from the Doctrine of your Salvation, that more ſure Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie; and ſo your Faith will ſtand not on the Wiſdom of Men, but on the Power of GOD. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 5</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="biography">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:37760:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Life and Death of Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall, <hi>who died</hi> April 13. Anno Dom. 1665.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THomas Hall</hi> was born in St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> in the City of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> about <hi>July</hi> 22. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1610. His Father was Mr. <hi>Richard Hall,</hi> a Cloathier in that City, of a competent Eſtate, his Mother was Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Bonner,</hi> deſcended of an antient Family; but that which truly ennobled her was with the <hi>Bereans,</hi> ſhe <note place="margin">Acts 17. 11.</note> diligently ſearched the Scriptures. Theſe two lived together many years, God giving them a plentiful Progeny of Sons and Daughters: three of which Sons were brought up Scholars, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards proved godly Preachers<hi>:</hi> The Mother being to them (as an <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> or <hi>Monica</hi> to <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.5.</note> a careful Inſtructer in their Youth and lived to reap the Fruit of her endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in her old age <hi>(Magnum eſt Dei beneficium pios nanciſci Parentes, ac prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertim</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:37760:46"/>
                     <hi>Matrem qua pene tota filio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">A lapide.</note> 
                     <hi>educatio dependet),</hi> like another <hi>Bathſheba</hi> ſhe did bathe them with her Tears and Inſtructions, and with her <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 2</note> warm and melting Supplications.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Thomas</hi> was firſt ſet to the Grammar-School under Mr. <hi>Bright,</hi> and thence ſent to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and admitted into <hi>Bayliole</hi> Colledg; whence (through the neglect of his Tutor) he removed to <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and became Pupil to Dr. <hi>Luſhington,</hi> a good Scholar; but whoſe Principles <note place="margin">As <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith of him.</note> were ſo poyſonous, that he might have boaſted with <hi>Protagoras,</hi> that he had ſpent many years in corrupting of youth.</p>
                  <p>Having taken his Degrees, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the Country, and for a while preached and taught a private School, at the Chappels belonging to <hi>Kings-Norton.</hi> But as yet he was a Foe and no Friend to Gods Truth and People, whom he oppoſed under the notion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Puritans. But as it was with <hi>St. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> (who before was vitious in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and erronious in judgment) going to hear the Eloquence of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> was reduced from his Errours<hi>:</hi> ſo it fared
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37760:46"/>
with him, being about that time a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent frequenter of the learned Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of ſundry Orthodox Divines at <hi>Burmingham;</hi> he had here a ſure and ſafe foundation laid of the true Religion; and from that time, he favoured the ſincere Milk of the Word of God, and intirely loved thoſe that were born and begotten unto God thereby.</p>
                  <p>Not long after he was called to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Cure at <hi>Kings-norton,</hi> under his Brother Mr. <hi>John Hall,</hi> who had it annexed to the Vicarage of <hi>Bromsgrove,</hi> and a while after gave it franckly to him; the Free-School was alſo added to it, for his further encouragement; (for though it were a large Pariſh, yet the great Tyths being impropriate) he had but a ſmall Sallary, and could ſcarcely have ſubſiſted, had he not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced a ſingle life for this cauſe chiefly as he ſaid. Yet after God had ſet a ſeal to his Miniſtry, this great people were much upon his heart (who ever ſought Work rather than Wages) that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be perſwaded to leave them, though ſolicited with a promiſe of far greater preferment, and was in the time of War often accuſed, curſed, threatned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37760:47"/>
with death, plundred many times, and five times impriſoned at the leaſt.</p>
                  <p>He was a very hard Student, though of a cold rheumatick Conſtitution; he would <hi>impalleſcere Chartis,</hi> even hazard his life to get Learning and the choice Obſervations he met with in good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, he inſerted into his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place Book, and by his great induſtry he acquired a good meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in Arts and Sciences, eſpecially in Divinity; of God and his Word, and Works; of himſelf and his Duty; <note place="margin">Plin. Sec. de Avun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo ſuo Epiſt. l. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Perire omne tempus arbitrabatur quod ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis non impertiretur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He took great pains in his Paſtoral Charge, and would not offer to God that which coſt him nothing: he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly preached twice on the Lords day, and kept Lectures in other places; beſides his Expoſition of Scripture, and Catechizing, which laſt he uſed when the days were of any length, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways before the Sacrament; and many of his Hearers ſent in their Children and Servants to be inſtructed: To which he added private Admonition, Prayer and Examination to many that were willing to partake of that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37760:47"/>
yet were unwilling to appear in publick: by all which means he did much good, and laid ſuch a foundation that few of his Hearers were levened with the looſe opinions of thoſe times.</p>
                  <p>And ſo great was his repute amongſt the godly, that many came to hear him from far, and not a few deſired his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in their fears, doubts and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and ſeveral perſons of Quality ſent their Sons to table in the houſe with him, that they might partake of his prayers and precepts for the orderly regulating of their lives and ſeaſoning their tender years; eſpecially ſuch as intended them for the Miniſtry, to the intent that they might get Learning, a right Method in their Studies, and learn to divide the Word of Truth aright; whoſe pains hath been to ſo good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that many of his Scholars have proved able Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Neither was his Good confined to a particular Congregation; for he ſeemed with the Apoſtle to have a care of all the Churches; and it might be ſaid of him, as of <hi>Calvin,</hi> That he was no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affected towards the Churches of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37760:48"/>
Chriſt though remote, than if he bore them upon his ſhoulders. How pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically would he pray for the Churches abroad, and ſympathize with them in their ſorrows and ſufferings! and when he heard good news from far of any Church of Chriſt planted, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel propagated any-where, How would he rejoice and praiſe God! and even particular Churches at home in many places have taſted of his good will, by his preaching and prayers.</p>
                  <p>But to ſpeak of him more expreſly and particularly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He was a man of great integrity and ſingle-heartedneſs in his Miniſtry, eſpecially, wherein he had no worldly or baſe affection, no carnal deſign or ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſt, mainly ſeeking the glory of God, the good of his Flock, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring always this, before any earthly gain or advantage whatſoever: in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and godly ſincerity he had his Converſation in this preſent world. He <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.</note> earneſtly coveted the beſt things; and if any worldly thing, it was Books; as Dr. <hi>Smith</hi> would ſay merrily of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Nullius rei preterquam Librorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varus;</hi> he coveted nothing but Books:
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37760:48"/>
and not Books neither ſo much for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <note place="margin">He made not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the center of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> as for the publick good<hi>:</hi> Witneſs the Library at <hi>Burmingham</hi> and <hi>Kings<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norton:</hi> The Latter of which that he might procure the Pariſh to Build, he gave his Study of Books to it in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time<hi>:</hi> to the former he was a good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor, and gave ſeveral Volumes that he bought, and prevailed with many of his Brethren to do the like.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He was of a free and liberal heart, never thinking the things that he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed <note place="margin">Acts 2.44.</note> were his own, or that he was born for himſelf, but for his Country and the Church of God. In his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time he made his own hands his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors; like Noble <hi>Arawna</hi> he would give like a King, or as the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> according to his power; yea, even <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> beyond his power; and always he gave his Heart with the Gift: if he beheld a poor man that wanted Cloaths for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Family, How would his very bowels yearn towards them! and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>T. H.</hi> His true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> he he hath been ſeen to pluck the very Coat off his own back to cloath ſuch.</p>
                  <p>And though he uſually denied not ſuch as asked an Alms of him in the <note place="margin">As it was ſaid of Mr. <hi>Fox.</hi>
                     </note> Name of Chriſt, yet the nearer any
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37760:49"/>
were to God, the more they taſted of his bounty; knowing it was his duty to do good to all, <hi>eſpecially to the hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
                     <hi>of Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. He was a juſt man, and lived much by Faith when outward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 38.</note> failed; for when he had expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded moſt he had upon charitable uſes, his uſual ſaying was, <hi>enough; enough:</hi> And in his laſt ſickneſs, when he had but ſix pence in his Purſe, and a Friend offered to lend him Money, he refuſed it; and not long after God ſo enlarged the hearts of his people towards him, that he had ſeveral ſealed Papers of Money ſent him, as I am credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, he knew not from whence; So that he had enough indeed, and to ſpare. <hi>Eſau</hi> could ſay he had enough, but <hi>Jacob</hi> had more, or had all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God was his Portion; he had enough to give Legacies to certain Friends after his Burial. It fared with him, as with <hi>Pithias</hi> a Merchant of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaca,</hi> who had compaſſion upon an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Man taken by Pirates, and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him, and bought the Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they had taken from him; the old Man ſaw that out of meer pity and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37760:49"/>
charity he had done this, he diſcovered a great Maſs of Money hidden amongſt certain Barrels of Pitch, that he had bought of theſe Pirates, inſomuch as the Merchant became very rich: So this our ſpiritual Merchant loſt not but gained by laying up his Treaſure in Heaven; he thought that <hi>depoſitum</hi> better in Gods hand than in his own. As the Widows Meal in the Barrel and Oyl in the Cruiſe waſted not, but increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by feeding the Prophet; ſo he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his Bread upon the Waters, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it after many days.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He was a Man of an holy and unbla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable life; ſo that Malice it ſelf, though it might bark at him, yet could not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten her Teeth upon him. He was not like ſome Preachers now-adays, who bid the people <hi>do as they ſay, but not as they do:</hi> For what he impoſed on the people as a Duty, he made it his ſtudy and endeavour to practiſe. That Holineſs that he ſo excellently diſplayed <note place="margin">See his beauty of Holineſs.</note> from the Pulpit, was not ſimply notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal but affective, and had an influence into his life; you who were of his Charge are Witneſſes, and God alſo; <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2. 10, 11, 12.</note> how holily and juſtly, and unblamably he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37760:50"/>
behaved himſelf amongſt you, how he exhorted, and comforted, and charged every one as a Father doth his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that you would walk worthy of him that hath called you: And when the Book for Sports and Recreations on the Lords Day came forth, though en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined to be read by publick Authority in the ſeveral Churches throughout the Land, he deeming it a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of the Sabbath, and contrary to the Word of God, refuſed to read it, <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 4.</note> though he was threatned for it<hi>:</hi> for which he ſuppoſed he had our Saviour his Precept, and his Apoſtles Practice <note place="margin">Acts 5.29.</note> in ſuch a caſe to obey God rather than Man. And what <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 4. 19.</note> was true of him; <hi>Non leve preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium eſt, tantam eſſe Morum integrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ut ne hoſtes reperiant quod calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entur;</hi> His life was ſo unblameable that his greateſt Enemies could not blemiſh him.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He was of an humble deportment and carriage, eaſie of acceſs, and eaſie to be intreated: he had not reſpect to the rich, becauſe of their riches, nor deſpiſed the poor, becauſe of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty; but his doors and ears were open
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37760:50"/>
to them, and he would be an Advocate for them, and plead their cauſe with ſuch as were mightier than they; and the meaneſt Inhabitant of the Pariſh ſhould aſſoon have his requeſt granted, if lawful and in his power, as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. He ſought not after great things for himſelf, but was content with mean fare and coarſe cloathing; and would often uſe that ſaying of Mr. <hi>Greenham,</hi> brown Bread and the Goſpel is good fare; and if his Landlady had provided any Diſh that he thought ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, he could hardly be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to taſte of it, but would blame her for it<hi>:</hi> And it ſeemed to import his deep humility, he gave order after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, That his Body ſhould neither be laid in the Church nor Chappel, but in the Church-yard among the meaneſt of his neighbours.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He was a great lover of peace; and for peace ſake hath often parted with his own right, never looking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly after Decimations, but leaving it to the people many times to do as they pleaſed, &amp; made compoſitions with them upon eaſie terms to their good liking: and when he heard of Contentions in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37760:51"/>
the Pariſh, he would preach againſt them, and perſwade his Hearers to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after the things that made for peace: And when any litigious actions have been brought in their own Court, he hath endeavoured to ſtop ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedures, ſhewing the parties that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, how unchriſtian a Courſe it was for them who were brethren to fall out amongſt themſelves; Eſteeming it much better to buy Love than Law, ſince <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dod.</hi>
                     </note> they might buy much Love for a little, but could not have a little Law for a great deal; yea though he prized peace at ſo high a rate, he would not part with purity to purchaſe it.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. His preaching was plain, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and powerful, not in the inticing words of mans wiſdom; and he ſpake not <hi>Phalerata,</hi> but <hi>fortia,</hi> in the evidence <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 1.</note> and demonſtration of the Spirit; never reſpecting the perſons of men, whether rich or poor, but reproved ſin in whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he ſaw it.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He was one that was much in Communion with God in publick and in private, according to his duty; and as the Churches neceſſity called for it, obſerving many days of Humiliation
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37760:51"/>
and Prayer with his own Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and other private Chriſtians, <note place="margin">Gen. 18.17</note> wherein he would reverently pour out his ſoul into the boſom of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and had much of Gods <note place="margin">Pſal. 25. 14.</note> mind made known to him; So that he did foretel what would befal this and our Neighbour Kingdoms for our ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be reformed; and in particular, that deſolation of <hi>London</hi> by Plague and Fire, before God ſet up thoſe Comers as Intelligencers to forewarn the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. See what he writ in his Epiſtle <note place="margin">Before his <hi>Samaria's</hi> Downfal.</note> to that famous City: <hi>Sin</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hath brought down greater Cities than yours; as they had their time of riſing, ſo of ruining; as of building, ſo of bruning; Witneſs</hi> Nineveh, Noe, Tyrus, Babylon <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>Sin hath made them all a deſolation. I ſhall never expect</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that City or State ſhall proſper, or that your houſes ſhould continue when Gods Houſe lies waſt; all our Buildings will be but</hi> Nods <hi>and</hi> Babels, <hi>unſettlement and confuſion till Gods Houſe be ſettled and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. He was abundant in thanksgiving to God, for calling him to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of his Will, and for giving him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:37760:52"/>
heart to imbrace the Truth in the love of it, who walked before as other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whom God hath paſſed by, though greater in Wealth, outward Worth, Wiſdom, Learning; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he had called him to the work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, in a place according to his own heart, and among ſuch a people as bore good will to his perſon, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging this to be the meer good pleaſure of God, he endeavoured to quicken himſelf and his Flock to a grateful Conſideration of the love of God in this reſpect.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. He was very careful how he ſpent his time, which he never did in idleneſs, unneceſſary journeys, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental viſits, but whitherſoever he went, his intention was either to do or receive good: that time that he could ſpare from his Paſtoral Employment, he ſpent moſtly in viſiting of Learned men and in writing Books; Thirteen of which he printed in his life-time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what he left for the Preſs after his Death.</p>
                  <p>Concerning that Commentary of his upon the Second of <hi>Timothy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ley</hi> a very Learned, Godly Man writeth;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37760:52"/>
                     <hi>That it is the better half</hi> (not in quantity only, but in quality) <hi>of the beſt Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Treatiſes that he had ſeen upon that Scripture; And doth believe for Congruity of the Truth with the holy Text, perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and fulneſs of profitable matter, (deducted from it or conſonant to it) is the beſt that hitherto hath been Extant in the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am now arrived at the laſt Scene of his Life, and the beginning of his Sickneſs; no part of which he acted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, admitting of common frailties, which are incident to the beſt of Saints, who ſhould be denominated <hi>ſecundu n meliorem partem,</hi> with ſome Grains of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance; (As Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſaith,) <hi>A Pomegranate without any Core, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be planted in Paradiſe;</hi> And as the Swan is ſaid to ſing moſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he is dying and exchanging life <note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> for death; Of which Bird <hi>Martial</hi> hath this Epigram:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Dulcia defecta modulatur Carmina lingua,</l>
                     <l>Cantator Cygnus funeris ipſe ſui.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sweet ſtrains he chanteth out with's dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongue,</l>
                     <l>And is the Singer of his Funeral Song.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:37760:53"/>
So this Saint and Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, as he was profitable in his life; ſo he was peaceable and pleaſant in his ſickneſs, ſinging and making melody in his heart unto the Lord.</p>
                  <p>In the year 1664, about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>September,</hi> before his laſt ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as he was going up the ſtairs to his Study, he was ſmitten as if one had ſtruck him with a Dagger on his back; inſomuch that he was not ſatisfied, till they that were near him looked to ſee whether there were any viſible here; he was nigh fainting upon it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued weak: before this he had been viſited with a Quartain Ague, the Dregs of which Diſeaſe being not wrought out by Phyſick, brought a lingring <hi>Scorbute,</hi> and he felt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream pain in his back, and had a Flux of Blood iſſuing from him, which brought him very weak; yet he was ſtrong in the Lord and in the power of his might, and did mightily admire the free Grace of God in Chriſt, in ſeparating him from his Mothers womb, calling him by his grace, and ſetting him apart for the work of the Miniſtry, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that high and holy Calling; ſo
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37760:53"/>
many that walked worthy of their profeſſion, and received with the heart the form of Doctrine delivered to them. And in his Sickneſs, though ſometimes he might be heard to groan, yet never to grumble; but would always juſtifie God, and condemn himſelf; and ſoon ſilence any mutinous and murmuring thoughts that might ſeem to ariſe in his heart, upon their firſt ſallying forth; In the words of the Prophet, <hi>Shall a man receive good from the hands of the Lord, and not evil?</hi> He counted his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and his ſufferings light and momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, the glory to come, weighty, great, and ſo joyous, as too big to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the ſoul, that the ſoul muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it; often mentioning that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Apoſtle; For <hi>our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction which is but for a moment, worketh</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>unto us a far more exceeding weight of glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>March</hi> 22. 1665, his dear ſiſter Mrs. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leanor Smith</hi> came to viſit him, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon him to the very day of his death, and wrote down in her Book the moſt remarkable paſſages that ſhe heard from him: Many of which you will have wound up in the enſuing Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:37760:54"/>
(He ſaid) he had done his work (meaning that he had run the courſe of his Miniſtry, and accompliſhed that laſt Work of his upon the ſeventy-firſt Pſalm) and now longed for his Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, <note place="margin">Pſal. 71.</note> and to reſt with his dear Lord Jeſus; And though he rejoiced much that he had compleated his former Works, yet this was the quinteſſence of all, that he was going to receive his Reward; and counted not his life dear unto him, ſince he ſhould ſhortly ſee the lovely face of his dear Saviour. And as <hi>St. Auguſtine,</hi> when he meditated of that paſſage of God to <hi>Moſes, Thou ſhalt not ſee my face and live; Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>then</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Tunc mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riar ut te videam.</note> 
                     <hi>let me die that I may ſee thy face:</hi> So this ſerious and ſincere Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, having ſeen him by the eye of Faith, was now ready to ſing old <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meons Nunc Dimittis; Lord, now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in peace.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing troubled him ſo much, as that he was going to a place where he was to have ſo great Wages for ſo little Work. And he not only at the laſt (as it was ſaid to be the Speech of <hi>Bellarmine)</hi> upon his Death-bed, <hi>Tutiſſimam eſt iter ad Coelum per merita Chriſti;</hi> but he
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37760:54"/>
wholly in his health and ſickneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied on Chriſt for Juſtification, Life and Salvation, freely by Faith in his Blood. <note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>He told Mrs. <hi>Smith,</hi> he much rejoiced at her kind coming to him, eſpecially at the hopes he had of her continuance with him to the laſt; which might be a means to free him from all ſcandals that might be caſt upon him by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts or Quakers, who he knew would ſpare him no leſs at his Death, than they had done in his life: he thought they would not ſtick to ſay, he died raging, an Atheiſt, or a Papiſt, or caſt the like Calumnies upon him, as they did upon <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Calvin; But</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>being now in perfect memory, I do declare, I die a ſincere Servant of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and do deteſt from the bottom of my heart, all their erroneous Opinions and Practices.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>(He ſaid) <hi>he thought he had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as much conteſt with Satan, the World, and the Fleſh, as ever any man for his time; of which he had left a particular teſtimony to be printed with his other works.</hi> This was (I conceive) his Life writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his own hand, which I never had the happineſs to ſee, though I much
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37760:55"/>
ſought after it, for the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this his <hi>Narrative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He often did reflect upon the evil of the times, the reigning ſins, whereby God was diſhonoured; <hi>viz.</hi> Profaneneſs, Atheiſm, Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were very grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to him<hi>:</hi> and he took it as a choice Mercy, that God would take him out of the world (in ſuch a time as this); <hi>Lord,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>what am I, that thou ſhouldſt think on me, and give me reſt in ſuch an evil day?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He much deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed to wait upon the Lord without diſtraction and diffidence, knowing that his time was the beſt; but rather if it were the Lords will and pleaſure, he deſired to be out of the body, that <hi>mortality might be ſwallowed up of life;</hi> he would ſay; <hi>O Lord, how long, holy and juſt, why drive the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot-wheels on ſo heavily? I long Lord, to come unto thee!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as he was comfortable in his Sickneſs; ſo he gave much ſweet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and encouragement to Miniſters and private Chriſtians that came to viſit him, eſpecially to ſuch as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to God by his Miniſtry, or had fitted for the ſervice of God in his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37760:55"/>
Church. A reverend Doctor coming to ſee him, and ſpeaking comfortable words to him; he told him he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his reſt, and hoped the <hi>Church of God</hi> would have reſt; and that God would raiſe up and refreſh his faithful Servants in the Miniſtry; and though there might be a ſharp ſtorm coming, he conceived that it would be but ſhort. He adviſed his Viſitants to ſtand faſt in the Faith and not to ſhrink, though a trying time ſhould come, he would have them to continue conſtant to their Chriſtian calling, and not to be carried away with the errour of the wicked to forſake their ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to grow in grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> prepare for death and judgment.</p>
                  <p>A young Miniſter coming to ſee him, he exhorted him to adorn his Miniſtry with a holy life; which if he did not, he might do more harm by his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, than by all the Sermons he ſhould preach.</p>
                  <p>He called for the four Youths in the Family under his inſpection, and gave them wholſome inſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their Creatour in the days of their</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.1.</note> 
                     <hi>youth;</hi> he warned them to keep Gods
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37760:56"/>
watch, to abſtain from youthful luſts, to obſerve the Lords Day ſtrictly, and to be obedient to their Parents; which if they did, it would be well with them, and they ſhould be a bleſſing to Poſterity, and bid them remember theſe were the words of their dying Maſter, and ſo he bleſſed them particularly in the Name of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Ordinarily ſuch of his Pariſh that came to ſee him, he would caution them not to procraſtinate their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but to be ſerious in the matters of God and his Service, to break off all delays, and to embrace the tenders of grace, the motions of the Holy Spirit, and ſet upon the practice of good works, and to do nothing that might interrupt the peace of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which would witneſs for them or againſt them, teſtifying that what he had taught them, was the Truth of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>When ſome came to ſee him, that he conceived were addicted to ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſins, he would endeavour their Conviction, by pertinent Texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; as I heard him ſay to one, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to take heed of Covetouſneſs:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37760:56"/>
and ſo he would ſay of other ſins, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that it was the Counſel of their dying Miniſter.</p>
                  <p>I think I ſhall never forget his vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and benediction to my ſelf and my dear Brother, with his hearty Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Precepts: it put me in mind when I ſaw him in that poſture, of good old <hi>Jacob</hi> rearing himſelf upon his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, <note place="margin">Gen. 47. 31.</note> or leaning upon a Staff to bleſs his Children; Oh with what gravity and authority did he ſpeak, as if he were already in the Suburbs of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>When he perceived ſome to go away ſad from him, as lamenting his loſs; he would ſay, <hi>I am now going where I ſhall have reſt from Sin and Satan, from all fear, wearineſs, watching, and from all the evils and errors of a wicked world; even ſo</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Come Lord Jeſus; for I long for thy Coming.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When his pains grew greater, he oft prayed that God would help him to wait upon him without ſin.</p>
                  <p>He was abundant in praiſes to God, that he was pleaſed to take him away in that opportunity of time; as to the ſame purpoſe a little varied; he ſaid, <hi>If God had put a Pen into my hand, and</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:37760:57"/>
                     <hi>had bid me write the time I would die, I ſhould have wrote for this, before feebleneſs and diſability of old age took hold upon me; now my work is done, and to die in peace is a great mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come Lord</hi> (ſaid he), <hi>come away; for my deſires are wholly for thee, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thy Name: I am going to keep an everlaſting holy day to the Lord, a year of Jubilee is at hand;</hi> and here he fell into ſuch an extaſie of joy, and ſuch ſeraphical expreſſions he ſpake (as were thoſe that the Apoſtle heard in his rapture) which were hardly to be written, (his Siſter ſaid) they were <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> beyond her Pen.</p>
                  <p>He lay after this very meekly under his weakneſs, his body decaying apace; <note place="margin">April 20.</note> and he ſaid, <hi>he felt the ſymptoms of death,</hi> and then cried, <hi>when Lord, when wilt thou come?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having ſome intermiſſion from pain, he affirmed Satan ſaid to him, <hi>What doſt thou think to eſcape above all others? but</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I prayed the Lord to rebuke him, and ſo heard no more of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And when his Phyſician would have given him hopes that God might reſtore him to health, he would not hear of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37760:57"/>
that, but gave him good Counſel, and ſaid, <hi>He loved him much for the grace he ſaw in him, and for his care he had of him,</hi> and bid him <hi>prepare for a ſtorm, and keep his integrity for Chriſt, and he would keep him in the hour of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>(He ſaid) <hi>I bleſs God, I am going to better friends, to a better place, and better imployment; I long to be in it; When will it once be, Lord? not my time, but thine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After this, there came a Neighbour-Miniſter unto him, and ſaid, The Church of God would be a great loſer by his Death; he anſwered, <hi>he had done his Work, and God had better to raiſe up in his ſtead; and counted himſelf happy that he was going to his reſt, and ſhould ſee none of the evils that were coming; yet was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that God ſhould ſerve himſelf upon him, and then let him depart in peace, as</hi> David <hi>that ſerved his generation faithfully accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 13.36</note> 
                     <hi>to the will of God, ſlept with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Being asked what he thought of the Church of God, he anſwered, <hi>God was in the midſt of her, ſhe ſhould not be moved; God would keeep her, and that right early.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:37760:58"/>
When a friend asked him, how he did (he ſaid) <hi>never better; for I am going to God, but never worſe as to the outward man:</hi> and his Siſter offering him a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, he refuſed it, ſaying, <hi>Give no more now; for it is not fit that I ſhould be feaſting my body when I ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnally in Communion with Chriſt, and waiting with my Lamp ready trimmed; God feedeth me with better food than the world can afford me with.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He begged much that God would take him to keep an everlaſting Sabbath with himſelf; <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Job 19. 25, 26.</note> 
                     <hi>at the laſt day upon the earth: And though after my skin worms deſtroy this body, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh. Oh let my life be nothing but prayer and praiſes, ſince God hath dealt ſo tenderly with me.</hi> He often comforted himſelf with the glorious eſtate he had in hope, and that he had a company of Angels round about him to keep and guard him to his Fathers Houſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come Lord,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>carry me out of this weary houſe of clay, which is ſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to me; When, when wilt thou come, Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:37760:58"/>
He was as full of heavenly comfort as his heart could hold; yet not without ſome intervals of aſſaults, and Satans buffettings; for he ſaid, <hi>Siſter, Siſter, Did not I abhor the Maſs?</hi> Oh yes, ſaid ſhe, let not Satan tell you otherwiſe; for you have prayed and preached, and wrote againſt it, and now abhor it: to which he anſwered, <hi>I do, and do abhor it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A little after, he ſaid, <hi>God was coming to do wonders by the operation of his Spirit, it will be, it will be, go tell it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have nothing to do, but to die;</hi> and even whiles he lay with death-pangs upon him, he ſpake this; <hi>All the joys of this life are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> nothing to the joy I have in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> He cloſed up his Life, and breathed out his laſt breath, with theſe words; <hi>Come, Lord Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He died <hi>April</hi> 13. 1665. at 4 of the Clock in the Evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="by_the_same_author">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:37760:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Names of the Thirteen Books he Printed in his life-time,</hi> viz.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. THE Pulpit guarded, in <hi>quarto.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The Font guarded, 4<hi>to.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The Schools guarded, or a Defence of <hi>H. L.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. The Beauty of Holineſs, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. A Treatiſe againſt long Hair.</item>
                     <item>6. Wiſdoms Conqueſt, a Tranſl. of the <hi>13th</hi> Book of <hi>Ovids Metamorphoſis,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Phaetons</hi> Folly, a Tranſlation of the <hi>2d</hi> Book of <hi>Ovids Metamorphoſis,</hi> 8<hi>vo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. <hi>Hometius Enervatus;</hi> or a Treatiſe againſt the <hi>Millenaries.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. <hi>Sal Terrae;</hi> or a guard to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and their Maintenance.</item>
                     <item>10. An Expoſition by way of Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, chapters of the Prophecie of <hi>Amos.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. <hi>Samaria's</hi> Downfal; or a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary by way of Supplement, on the 5 laſt verſes of <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.</item>
                     <item>12. The Beauty of Magiſtracy, in an Expoſition of Pſalm 82. Wherein is ſet forth the neceſſity, utility, dignity, duty and morality of Magiſtrates.</item>
                     <item>13. A Practical and Polemical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary, or Expoſition upon the <hi>3d</hi> &amp; <hi>4th</hi> Chapters of the Latter Epiſtle of St <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>There is alſo Treatiſe a of his againſt May-poles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="elegy">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:37760:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Elegy upon the Death of that humble and holy Man of God, Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall.</head>
                  <l>WHat ayl'd pale Death in haſt to <hi>Hall</hi> away</l>
                  <l>Our reverend Paſtor to a bed of Clay! Tell me (bleſt Saint) in ſooth, how couldſt So great a Maſter in Divinity?</l>
                  <l>Could not (at leaſt) our ſighs, our pray'rs thou die</l>
                  <l>Prevail, that thou might'ſt live old <hi>Neſtors</hi> and tears</l>
                  <l>Injurious Fate! becauſe thou couldſt not get years?</l>
                  <l>The Pearl, Would'ſt therefore ſpoil the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet?</l>
                  <l>What wilt thou put no diff'rence 'twixt faces?</l>
                  <l>Not ſpare th' Saints for their tranſcendent graces?</l>
                  <l>Sure thou art neither blear'd, nor brib'd, nor blind,</l>
                  <l>Thou tak'ſt the beſt and leav'ſt the worſt behind.</l>
                  <l>T'ſhould ſeem from Death ther's no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription then,</l>
                  <l>The Preacher dies as well as other men.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:37760:60"/>
Had I but tears to ſpare, that are not ſpent</l>
                  <l>Upon my ſins! I would give Sorrow vent;</l>
                  <l>I'd drench the earth wherein his body lies,</l>
                  <l>And fill the air with Lamentable cries!</l>
                  <l>I'd wet his Coffin, and would waſh his Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Till I another <hi>Niobe</hi> become!</l>
                  <l>But ſtay (my Muſe) what means this Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</l>
                  <l>Sure his was not a Death but a tranſlation;</l>
                  <l>H'walk'd with God, and he hath took him hence,</l>
                  <l>Not to his loſs, but to his recompence<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And yet he lives, methinks I ſee him ſtill,</l>
                  <l>In's doing good, eſchewing what is ill;</l>
                  <l>'Specially in th' works he hath left behind,</l>
                  <l>The pious product of's Prophetick mind.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>London</hi> look to't, he foretold thy burning,</l>
                  <l>Thy Plague and poverty for not returning;</l>
                  <l>If Gods Houſe be not built within th' Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                  <l>Yours, and ours will be deſolation.</l>
                  <l>Seeing thoſe City-Comets that God ſent,</l>
                  <l>As in fiery Chariot t' Heaven he went:</l>
                  <l>Were't not Ambition, I could wiſh that he,</l>
                  <l>Had lay'd the lap of's Mantle on me.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Moore.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:37760:60"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Epitaph upon Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall.</head>
                  <l>WIthin the period of <hi>Davids</hi> Span,</l>
                  <l>Behold the Sepulture of this Grave man;</l>
                  <l>Who whiles he liv'd, fear'd not th'face of any</l>
                  <l>Good counſel living, dying, gave t' many;</l>
                  <l>And though he chaſtly led a ſingle life,</l>
                  <l>Held his School's Children, and his Church his Wife<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To which he did impart moſt liberally,</l>
                  <l>His Books in's life unto her Library;</l>
                  <l>The reſidue almoſt of what he had,</l>
                  <l>He gave the poor to make their faces glade.</l>
                  <l>Th' heaven born Jewel's gone; the Grave contains,</l>
                  <l>Within her womb, only thoſe few remains,</l>
                  <l>Which though entombed now, abide they may,</l>
                  <l>Unto the laſt reſurrection day;</l>
                  <l>The Soul will then again reſume this duſt</l>
                  <l>To the habitation of the Juſt.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:37760:61"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of that dear Servant of Jeſus Chriſt Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall.</head>
                  <l>THou need'ſt no Trophees to adorn thy Herſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy virtues ſerve t' imbalm thy Name in Verſe;</l>
                  <l>And this I'll ſay, ſince death hath ſtopt thy breath,</l>
                  <l>Thy life was Prieſt-like, Prince-like was thy Death.</l>
                  <l>In Truths defence thou waſt a brazen wall,</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt execrable hereſies a Mawl:</l>
                  <l>Witneſs thy Guards, which ſtill unrouted ſtand</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Tom Collier,</hi> and that ſooty band:</l>
                  <l>What Guard the Font, the Schools, and Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit too,</l>
                  <l>Which of your Mothers Sons have done like you?</l>
                  <l>But yet thy Comments writ on ſacred ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Moſt juſtly may deſerve the greater Glory;</l>
                  <l>On th' Prophets thoſe thy Lucubrations,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe on <hi>Paul</hi> Doctor of th' Nations</l>
                  <l>Live, and thy other works of Charity,</l>
                  <l>Now thou art dead, &amp; with God, follow thee.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe thou haſt begot, cry out, my Father!</l>
                  <l>Which by Sage advice to God did'ſt gather,</l>
                  <l>Some of all ſorts of theſe, it doth them eaſe,</l>
                  <l>To trail a tear at thy ſad Obſequies.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:37760:61"/>
With blubred cheeks and countenance wan,</l>
                  <l>They ſit and ſing this Epicedium:</l>
                  <l>Let ſad <hi>April</hi> ceaſe her wonted ſhowers,</l>
                  <l>And mornful <hi>May</hi> forbear t'yield its flowers,</l>
                  <l>Since this fair Flower's cropt, and with dry eye,</l>
                  <l>So many do ſlight this ſad Deſtiny.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Moore.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the much-lamented Death of Mr.</hi> John Ley, <hi>who was Chair-man of the Aſſembly of Divines, and late Rector of</hi> Solyhull. <hi>His Character.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THe grace of God which in thy name did ſhine,</l>
                  <l>Was a Divine Spark, like generous Wine,</l>
                  <l>Which was infus'd in thee without aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>Into thy heart and parts even in old age;</l>
                  <l>Which ſhews to all impartial Judges how,</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt kept the good wine until now.</l>
                  <l>How many Learned within the Nation,</l>
                  <l>Like Conduits run wine at th' Coronation,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe parts ſoon flag, grow flat, and faint, and waſt,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt thine like wine on th' LEE, when old do laſt.</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſon</hi> an old Diſciple's, rather</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:37760:62"/>
Like <hi>Moſes</hi> was this Reverend Father;</l>
                  <l>For in old age, he had a Sp'rit like him,</l>
                  <l>His ſtrength did not abate, nor's eyes wax dim;</l>
                  <l>His Pentateuch in th' tipes was partly ſeal'd,</l>
                  <l>Till by this Pen unvail'd, the truth reveal'd.</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian Sabbath was by him main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd</l>
                  <l>Againſt all ſorts, who would have it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan'd.</l>
                  <l>A learned Schoolman, much for moderation,</l>
                  <l>One able to give Laws for diſputation;</l>
                  <l>He was skill'd in th' Tongues, curious at his Pen,</l>
                  <l>A moſt juſt Cenſor, both of Books &amp; Men:</l>
                  <l>He was a Load-ſtone in's lovely Carri'ge,</l>
                  <l>An Adamant for unconquer'd courage<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He'd ſpeak the truth where ere he had bin,</l>
                  <l>And lov'd the perſon but reprov'd the ſin<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More than moſt are, from paſſion h' was free,</l>
                  <l>More mov'd to pity, than moſt are was he.</l>
                  <l>He weekly made proviſion for th' Poor,</l>
                  <l>That conſtantly attended at his Door:</l>
                  <l>He'd ſympathize with ſuch as were in bonds,</l>
                  <l>And had great skill in ſetting broken bones:</l>
                  <l>A rare Caſuiſt, and hath been ſent for far</l>
                  <l>Toth'ſick, to ſee what their diſtemperswere,</l>
                  <l>And how to heal them, by his heav'nly Art</l>
                  <l>H'hath powred balm to many a broken heart:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:37760:62"/>
And that which crowns the reſt, is yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>H' was high in parts, and lowly in his mind.</l>
                  <l>Like God he had reſpect to men,</l>
                  <l>After the Good he ſaw in them;</l>
                  <l>This was the chief ingredient for which,</l>
                  <l>He prized any perſon poor or rich;</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as theſe, if they had need of them;</l>
                  <l>Should have his heart, his horſe his purſe, his pen.</l>
                  <l>I wiſh no worſe to's Succeſſor than he,</l>
                  <l>Juſt ſuch another Rector there may be.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Moore.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the much-lamented Death of Mr.</hi> Burdal, <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel at</hi> Walſhall <hi>in</hi> Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-ſhire.</head>
                  <l>WHat art thou dead too, another <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> a healing <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and Bo'nerges;</l>
                  <l>Who could'ſt convert thy ſelf to every form</l>
                  <l>Of ſp'rit and ſpeech, thy flock to reform?</l>
                  <l>When Rhet'rick and Metaphyſicks would not do't,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſought'ſt by ſound words, to woo them to it:</l>
                  <l>Thy Speech was above Books or humane Art,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:37760:63"/>
Thou melt'ſt the ſtone in many frozen heart,</l>
                  <l>More hard than that thou fear'dſt would thee torment,</l>
                  <l>Till thy laſt ſand was run and breath was ſpent.</l>
                  <l>Theſe pains did not prevent thy powr'ful Preaching,</l>
                  <l>Or travel of thy mind in th' conſtant teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</l>
                  <l>And as thou trad'ſt with God in pray'rs and tears,</l>
                  <l>He gave thee a return above thy fears.</l>
                  <l>Thou dy'd'ſt in th' fiftieth year, with little pain,</l>
                  <l>And an eternal Life in Heaven did'ſt gain.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Moore.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:37760:63"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of that humble and holy Servant of Jeſus Chriſt Mr.</hi> Henry Field, <hi>born at</hi> Kings-norton, <hi>bred up under Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall, <hi>and ſent to</hi> Pembroke-Colledg <hi>in</hi> Oxford, <hi>and from thence removed to</hi> Chriſts-Colledg <hi>in</hi> Cambridg, <hi>where he was Fellow, and ſo preferred by the Honourable Earl of</hi> Mancheſter <hi>to be Paſtor of</hi> Uttington <hi>in</hi> Lincoln-ſhire.</head>
                  <l>GReat was the Jewel hid within this field,</l>
                  <l>A Pearl more precious, than the earth doth yield;</l>
                  <l>One grace ſurpaſſeth Gold and Gems as far,</l>
                  <l>As the Sun ſhining doth the brighter Star.</l>
                  <l>This parti-colour'd coat wrought ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</l>
                  <l>And caus'd thy brethrens envy, &amp; their hate<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That from thy place and people thou waſt ſent,</l>
                  <l>To ſuffer ſharp and ſevere 'priſonment<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Far worſe than that of <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the pit,</l>
                  <l>Who afterwards was ſold to th' <hi>Iſhmaelite;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And by that Merchant-man, who came from far,</l>
                  <l>To the Kings Provoſt-Martial <hi>Potiphar;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where he was proſperous, yet by the wile</l>
                  <l>Of her, who would by ſin his ſoul defile,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:37760:64"/>
Was ſtript of's coat, to keep his conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>His feet were fettr'd for his continence.</l>
                  <l>Tell me (bleſs'd Saint) what, was not this thy fate,</l>
                  <l>If thou waſt not far more unfortunate?</l>
                  <l>For in his bonds, good <hi>Joſeph</hi> was more free,</l>
                  <l>Who favour found, &amp; was loos'd honourably</l>
                  <l>But't was otherwiſe with thee (dear brother)</l>
                  <l>Who waſt ſent from one priſon to th' other,</l>
                  <l>'Till death by a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> did remove</l>
                  <l>Thy fleſh to th'earth, thy ſoul to heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</l>
                  <l>In thoſe thy bonds thou waſt ſo comfortable</l>
                  <l>As made adverſity amiable;</l>
                  <l>For Divine Truth was girdle to thy loyns,</l>
                  <l>And uprightneſs the breſt-plate of thy reins;</l>
                  <l>A Faith moſt firm, a ſhield of thy defence,</l>
                  <l>And an incomparable patience:</l>
                  <l>Hope was the only helmet of thy head,</l>
                  <l>The Goſpels peace did light thee to thy bed.</l>
                  <l>Thy feet thus ſhod, thou feareſt no ſurprize,</l>
                  <l>But could'ſt defend thy ſelf 'gainſt injuries.</l>
                  <l>Thou having gotten theſe to good degree,</l>
                  <l>Obtain'ſt a conqueſt over Calamity.</l>
                  <l>Sore were thy life's troubles, ſweet thy reſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſmel's as of a Field that God hath bleſt.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Richard Moore.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:37760:64"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Death of many Reverend Miniſters ſince</hi> Bartholomew, 1662.</head>
                  <l>IF paſſion be a ſpur to poetry,</l>
                  <l>Sure it ſhould teach me for to verifie,</l>
                  <l>Were there but Sympathy, who can but weep,</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſo many Paſtors laid to ſleep?</l>
                  <l>What ſhall the poor Sheep do, now theſe are dead,</l>
                  <l>But dread likewiſe they ſhall be ſcattered?</l>
                  <l>The Lord hath ſmitten many Cedars tall,</l>
                  <l>How ſhould poor poplars chuſe but fear a fall?</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Iſraels</hi> chariots and horſemen gone?</l>
                  <l>How ſhould we chuſe but weep, and make great moan?</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Aſh</hi> foreſeeing what a dearth would be,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Sions</hi> Seers, fell, fell down ſuddenly?</l>
                  <l>Although it proved his death, yet would he grieve,</l>
                  <l>And buried was on <hi>Barthol'mew</hi> Eve.</l>
                  <l>As father <hi>Ely</hi> bowed his aged head,</l>
                  <l>Firſt when the news came, thy two ſons are dead:</l>
                  <l>But when he heard once that the Ark was loſt,</l>
                  <l>It brake his heart, his neck, his life it coſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:37760:65"/>
                     <hi>Vines, Naulton, Cawdry, Calamy</hi> went hence,</l>
                  <l>Like Nard and Camphire, trees of Frankincenſe;</l>
                  <l>Still ſending forth their aromatick ſcent,</l>
                  <l>Till twice extinct from us, to Heaven they went:</l>
                  <l>Learned <hi>Vines</hi> went away as in a ſleep,</l>
                  <l>And Zealous <hi>Naulton,</hi> who was wont to weep;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Calamy</hi> for <hi>London</hi> he loved ſo well,</l>
                  <l>When in the Fire he heard her paſſing-Bell.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cawdry</hi> crowded on, <hi>Caryl, White</hi> and <hi>Strong,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gouge, Gataker, Hill, whitaker</hi> and <hi>Young,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gravely,</hi> judicious <hi>Burges</hi> and <hi>Hall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who was <hi>Tom-tell-troth, Baker</hi> and <hi>Burdall;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pale death, why do'ſt thou make ſuch haſte,</l>
                  <l>And the true Churches Treaſure waſte?</l>
                  <l>Tell me in truth, what is there no reprieve,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch renowned Worthies might ſurvive?</l>
                  <l>See that a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> thou grant,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch the Clergies benefit may'nt want:</l>
                  <l>Though thou accoſteſt them with ſwifteſt wing,</l>
                  <l>I'me well aſſured thou haſt loſt thy ſting;</l>
                  <l>They're now made more than conquerors ſince dead,</l>
                  <l>And are triumphant, who were conquered<hi>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their Captain Chriſt hath got the Victory,</l>
                  <l>And ſoon (O Death) will make an end of thee;</l>
                  <l>In the mean time, thou canſt not ſurely kill</l>
                  <l>A Child of God, but cure him of his ill:</l>
                  <l>His Soul's above thy reach, and in a trice</l>
                  <l>When once diſmiſs'd ſhall mount to Paradice,</l>
                  <l>Nor hurt the Body, only lay't to bed</l>
                  <l>In th' Grave or Coffin, where it's buried.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>RICHARD MOORE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:37760:65"/>
                  <head>De Immortalitate.</head>
                  <l>BRight Marble, nor the gilded Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents</l>
                  <l>Of valiant Heroes, nor the rare Contents</l>
                  <l>Of wealthy Monarchs ſhall out-laſt thy fame,</l>
                  <l>Immortal Scholar of eternal name:</l>
                  <l>Neither ſhall time, thy praiſes e'r divide,</l>
                  <l>As learned yet as e'r was on our ſide.</l>
                  <l>Fierce <hi>Mars</hi> his Sword may Statues over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</l>
                  <l>And wealthy Cities into Aſhes burn,</l>
                  <l>Spoil and deface the works of coſtly plates,</l>
                  <l>High Spires and Temples prized at dear rates;</l>
                  <l>Yet cannot blur, nor theſe thy Works o'return</l>
                  <l>Immortal <hi>Hall,</hi> who ſleepeſt in thine Urn:</l>
                  <l>Art dead, do'ſt ſpeak by Books thou'ſt left behind,</l>
                  <l>Sight to the faithful, eyes unto the blind,</l>
                  <l>Bright Orient Pearls, to light through miſty vales,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:37760:66"/>
O're gloomy Mountains, and obſcureſt dales.</l>
                  <l>When Kingdoms are o'return'd like <hi>Troys</hi> ſad Town,</l>
                  <l>The brighteſt Gem thy lofty front ſhall crown,</l>
                  <l>Poſterity <hi>Halls</hi> learned Name ſhall boaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>When this our Iſle and <hi>Europe</hi> quite is loſt.</l>
                  <q>Aeternitati Comparatum omne tempus breve.</q>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Popham Gardiner.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <head>
                     <hi>An Epitaph on the never-to-be-forgotten Divine Mr.</hi> Thomas Hall.</head>
                  <l>STay Paſſenger in this cold duſty Urn,</l>
                  <l>Read carefully, in reading ſee thou learn</l>
                  <l>Life's brevity, the ſhortneſs of mans days,</l>
                  <l>How ſoon his glory fadeth and decays;</l>
                  <l>How ſoon his honour's brought unto the Grave,</l>
                  <l>How ſoon the worms their ſatisfaction have:</l>
                  <l>What does his Learning him at all avail,</l>
                  <l>When once his vital Spirits dying fail.</l>
                  <l>If literature could free learn'd Men from death,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:37760:66"/>
This <hi>Golgotha</hi> and dormentorious earth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Halls</hi> Skeleton ſhould never yet have found,</l>
                  <l>Who did with copious works ſo well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Genius</hi> of art, thy loſs we do lament,</l>
                  <l>Mellifluous Orator who ſtill time ſpent</l>
                  <l>In reading, ſeeking, hearing ſapience;</l>
                  <l>But now alas from us he is ſnatcht hence:</l>
                  <l>That makes us weep, weeping we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore,</l>
                  <l>Tears blur our writings, we can write no more.</l>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:37760:67"/>
                  <head>Life's Shortneſs.</head>
                  <l>Life's a bubble</l>
                  <l>Full of trouble,</l>
                  <l>And a vapour</l>
                  <l>Or a tapour:</l>
                  <l>Life's a flower</l>
                  <l>Laſts an hour,</l>
                  <l>Soon it blaſteth</l>
                  <l>Sooner waſteth.</l>
                  <l>Then think how ſoon Mans pleaſures fly away,</l>
                  <l>Since all his life-times but a winters day;</l>
                  <l>Like to the flower that with the Suns upriſe</l>
                  <l>His bud unfolds, and in the ev'ning dies;</l>
                  <l>His ſwift concurrent motions like th' Sun</l>
                  <l>With winged paces ſuddenly are gone.</l>
                  <l>Then think on God, on griſly death's ſtrong hand,</l>
                  <l>How thy poor ſoul at Gods juſt bar muſt ſtand;</l>
                  <l>Therefore prepare, his aid ſee thou im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore,</l>
                  <l>When that thou com'ſt his bar to ſtand before.</l>
                  <l>
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <bibl>
                           <hi>Solon.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </q>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:37760:67"/>
Have God in mind, him ſerve with filial fear,</l>
                  <l>And think how ſoon thy dying time is near;</l>
                  <l>Lord ſhall my ſoul when body it doth die</l>
                  <l>Lord-liking climb the heavens Canopie?</l>
                  <l>Then farewel Earth,</l>
                  <l>Place of my Birth,</l>
                  <l>Adieu vain Pleaſures,</l>
                  <l>Heaven yieldeth Treaſures,</l>
                  <l>Far better than this tottring Stage doth yield,</l>
                  <l>Where we can't act, but preſently are kill'd.</l>
                  <l>O griſly pale-fac't death why ſo unkind,</l>
                  <l>To take him hence, and leave me here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I am not ripe, too green of years</l>
                  <l>To full this Corn-field of deſtroying tares;</l>
                  <l>If t' were not ſo, thou wouldeſt take me hence</l>
                  <l>To Heaven above, thy dear's ones re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence;</l>
                  <l>Where Saints do triumph when the prize they've won,</l>
                  <l>When this my body may out-ſhine the Sun,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Moſes-like</hi> I view the three in one.</l>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37760:68"/>
            <head>Books to be Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and three <hi>Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>In <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>SErmons upon the whole Epiſtle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi> By Mr. <hi>John Daille,</hi> tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>F. S.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An Expoſition of Temptation, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 4, <hi>v.</hi> 1, to the end of the 11 <hi>v.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A practical Expoſition on the third Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of St <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with the <hi>Godly Mans Choice,</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8. By <hi>Anthony Burgeſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Forty ſix Sermons upon the whole Eight Chapter of the Epiſtle of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 Sermons upon the whole fourth Pſalm.</item>
               <item>10 Sermons upon the whole forty ſecond Pſalm.</item>
               <item>19 Sermons upon the whole 51 Pſalm.</item>
               <item>9 Sermons upon the whole 83 Pſalm. All Five; by <hi>Tho. Horton,</hi> D. D. Left perfected for the Preſs under his own Hand a little before his Death.</item>
               <item>XXVI Sermons upon ſeveral Texts of Scriptures. By the Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>John Donne,</hi> D. D.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:37760:68"/>
               <head>Quarto's.</head>
               <item>The Morning-Exerciſe againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, or the principal Errours of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Detected and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a Morning-Lecture, preached lately in <hi>Southwark.</hi> By ſeveral Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel in or near <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mediocria,</hi> or the moſt natural and plain underſtanding according to the Scripture of the great Doctrines of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, Redemption, Juſtification, the Covenants, the Law and Goſpel, and of Perfection.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Large Octavo.</head>
               <item>Captives bound in Chains, made free by Chriſt their Surety; or the Miſery of graceleſs Sinners, and their Recovery by Chriſt their Saviour. By <hi>Tho. Doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>littel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Faithfulneſs of God conſidered and cleared in the great Events of his Word; or a ſecond Part of the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Scripture. By the ſame Author.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Speculum Sherlockianum,</hi> or a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glaſs, in which the Admirers of Mr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> may behold the Man, as to his Accuracy, Judgment, Orthodoxy.</item>
               <item>The Childs Delight, together with an Engliſh Grammar.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37760:69"/>
The true way of reading and ſpelling Engliſh. Both by <hi>Tho. Lye.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Small Octavo.</head>
               <item>A Religious Family; or a Treatiſe, in which is, 1. The Beauty and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of a pious and well-ordered Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily deſcribed. 2. The ſingle Mans Family-Book faithfully preſcribed. By <hi>Phil. Lamb.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Index Biblicus Multijugus;</hi> or a Table to the Holy Scripture, wherein each of its Books, Chapters and divers Matters are diſtinguiſhed and epitomized.</item>
               <item>The almoſt-Chriſtian Diſcovered; or the Falſe-Profeſſor tried and caſt. By <hi>Matth. Mead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Godly Mans Ark; or the City of Refuge in the Day of his Diſtreſs, with Mrs. <hi>Moores</hi> Evidences for Heaven. By <hi>Edm. Calamy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The true Bounds of Chriſtian-Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. By <hi>S. Bolton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſinfulneſs of Sin and the Fulneſs of Chriſt. By <hi>Will. Bridge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe againſt Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or an Anſwer to the ordinary Queſtion, whether a Man may be ſaved in the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Religion. By <hi>I. C.</hi> D. D.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:37760:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
